<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The book of the Song of Solomon in meeter with some brief observations from the text, something pleasant, but more profitable to the unprejudiced reader, who loves the knowledge of God, and hath his heart inflam'd with the love of the Lord Jesus / by T.S. ...</title>
            <author>T. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15802499</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15802499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27986)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1166:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The book of the Song of Solomon in meeter with some brief observations from the text, something pleasant, but more profitable to the unprejudiced reader, who loves the knowledge of God, and hath his heart inflam'd with the love of the Lord Jesus / by T.S. ...</title>
                  <author>T. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The book of Jonah in meetre": p. 33-66.</note>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [7]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jonah --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BOOK OF THE SONG OF SOLOMON IN MEETER.</p>
            <p>WITH Some Brief Obſervations from the Text, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſant, but more profitable to the Unprejudiced Reader, who loves the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and hath his heart inflam'd with the Love of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. S.</hi> Who loveth, and could willingly ſerve any that Loves our Lord Jeſus in Sincerity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at the Signe of the Elephant and Caſtle near the Royall Exchange in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <l>THis is the firſt time ever I came forth</l>
            <l>To publique view: I now was very loath</l>
            <l>To have appear'd: but being often preſt</l>
            <l>By ſeveral Friends, at laſt at their requeſt,</l>
            <l>What by theſe Poems, was my firſt intention</l>
            <l>I finde (by theirs) doth meet with its prevention;</l>
            <l>For now and then according to my leiſure,</l>
            <l>I thought to reade, what I had writ with pleaſure;</l>
            <l>For to delight my ſelf it was my end,</l>
            <l>When firſt of all theſe Poems I had pen'd;</l>
            <l>But further here and there, now they muſt go,</l>
            <l>For why? 'tis providence, doth order 't ſo:</l>
            <l>They muſt abroad, though entertainment kinde</l>
            <l>I do not ſay that they ſhall always finde;</l>
            <l>For why? I know it is the common guiſe</l>
            <l>Of worldly wiſemen others to deſpiſe</l>
            <l>That are unlearn'd, although they have their learning</l>
            <l>From Chriſt alone, whereby they have diſcerning</l>
            <l>'Twixt things that differ: and for all the ſchools</l>
            <l>Of humane learning, men are ſtill but fools</l>
            <l>Till Chriſt be learned: nothing do they know</l>
            <l>And knowing nothing nothing can they do,</l>
            <l>As they ſhould do it: anſwering Gods command;</l>
            <l>May then the worldly wiſe man underſtand</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:3"/>
            <l>That he's the wiſe man that obeys the Lord,</l>
            <l>And with his laws, his life doth ſtill accord;</l>
            <l>Such promis't are to know the fathers minde,</l>
            <l>When worldly wiſemen ſeek, and cannot finde:</l>
            <l>Yet do I not in this i'th leaſt deſpiſe</l>
            <l>Learning it ſelf: nor yet the learned-wiſe;</l>
            <l>I hope no wiſe man then will take offence</l>
            <l>For unto both I give due reverence:</l>
            <l>Let none that reads theſe lines the ſame deſpiſe,</l>
            <l>B'cauſe in high flouriſhes I do not riſe;</l>
            <l>For it's a task a deal beyond my pains</l>
            <l>To ſoar aloft in ſuch affecting ſtrains</l>
            <l>As ſome that curious are would have: but I</l>
            <l>Am well content much lower for to lye.</l>
            <l>And ſith the ſubject of this my diſcourſe</l>
            <l>It is divine: what can I make it worſe,</l>
            <l>Becauſe I do not paint it in that dreſs</l>
            <l>Of Eloquence? what can it be the leſs</l>
            <l>Sacred for that? ſuch eloquence but feedeth</l>
            <l>The outward our: none ſuch as that is needed</l>
            <l>For of it ſelf it's garniſht with ſuch glory</l>
            <l>To parallel the ſame there wants a ſtory;</l>
            <l>The higheſt ſtrains, the moſt ſublimeſt wit</l>
            <l>Muſt lowr their topſayl, and bow down to it.</l>
            <l>The ſtile, the matter, method, and the words</l>
            <l>Are high and acurate, the world affords</l>
            <l>No Volumes that with it may once compare,</l>
            <l>It is more excellent then all they are:</l>
            <l>Here maiſt thou ſee that great tranſcendant love</l>
            <l>Chriſt bears his Church; which doth ſurmount above</l>
            <l>All other carnal earthly love as far</l>
            <l>As th' ſun aſcends above the loweſt Star;</l>
            <l>The great delight and pleaſure he takes in</l>
            <l>The ſouls that are purg'd throughly from their ſin:</l>
            <l>Here maieſt thou ſee alſo the ſpecial care</l>
            <l>He takes of them, each good thing to prepare,</l>
            <l>To fill their hearts with comforts and with joy,</l>
            <l>And bear them up in depths of miſery,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:3"/>
            <l>And when th'ave done what they have here to do,</l>
            <l>He will beſtow upon them heaven too;</l>
            <l>Here maiſt thou ſee alſo how ready ſtill</l>
            <l>Each gracious ſoul is dayly to fulfil</l>
            <l>What Chriſt commands: for love doth them conſtrain</l>
            <l>He loves them firſt, they love him back again:</l>
            <l>They love him ſo, they'l both ſuffer and do</l>
            <l>Whatever thing he's pleaſ'd to call them to:</l>
            <l>Here maiſt thou ſee the preſence of their Lord,</l>
            <l>The greateſt comforts to their ſouls afford:</l>
            <l>But if at any time away he's gone,</l>
            <l>The ſoul that wants him then doth ſigh and groan:</l>
            <l>And ſeeks, and ſues, and never is at reſt,</l>
            <l>Till with his preſence he again is bleſt;</l>
            <l>Here maiſt thou ſee how that Chriſts lovely ſpouſe,</l>
            <l>Doth ſleep and ſlug ſometimes, till be do rouze,</l>
            <l>And raiſe her up: ſhe doth a ſlumber catch</l>
            <l>But rais'd by Chriſt; ſhe ſtands upon her watch:</l>
            <l>Here ſee alſo the love that truly tyes</l>
            <l>A ſoul to Chriſt, it lives and never dyes:</l>
            <l>And how with earneſtneſſe ſuch pray to be</l>
            <l>With Jeſus Chriſt in full felicity.</l>
            <l>Reade ſoberly, and ponder what thou read'ſt</l>
            <l>Digeſt it well, and then thou'lt finde it feeds</l>
            <l>Thy inner man, but if thou fooliſhly</l>
            <l>Look on theſe Poems with a wanton eye,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe and ſatisfy a carnal minde</l>
            <l>No good unto thy ſoul then thou ſhalt finde;</l>
            <l>Take heed, and prove neither profane nor looſe,</l>
            <l>Bringing theſe Poems into great abuſe:</l>
            <l>Of wanton love they treat not in the leaſt,</l>
            <l>But of that love divine; which Chriſt is pleas'd</l>
            <l>In ſignes, in tipes, and figures to make known,</l>
            <l>Then reade full ſoberly; or elſe reade none:</l>
            <l>Well, I have done, I am expos'd unto</l>
            <l>The cenſures of them all; theſe papers view,</l>
            <l>If I have err'd in any thing, then know</l>
            <l>That every ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> may do ſo:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:4"/>
            <l>Since <hi>Adam</hi> fell, infallibilitie</l>
            <l>Is found in none, much leſs not found in me.</l>
            <l>If any one that reades ſome profit gains,</l>
            <l>Then am I well rewarded for my pains.</l>
            <l>If any ſcoff or jeer, go on and ſpare not,</l>
            <l>For ſome mens ſcoffs and jeers know that I care not,</l>
            <l>I am not rais'd by any flatteries,</l>
            <l>Nor yet caſt down becauſe ſome do not prize</l>
            <l>What I have writ: no, there is nothing leſs</l>
            <l>Shall trouble me, for ſtill I am</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:104634:4"/>
            <head>The Reader is Deſired to Correct theſe ſeverall Eſcapes in Printing this Book.</head>
            <p>IN the Preface <hi>p.</hi> 2. l. 20. for <hi>is needed</hi> r. <hi>it needeth.</hi> In the Book p. 1. l. 3. after <hi>Gods</hi> put in <hi>good.</hi> p. 6. l. 15. for <hi>are</hi> r. <hi>me.</hi> p. 7. l. 1. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>though.</hi> ib. l. 19. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>thy.</hi> p. 10. l. 29. in marg. for <hi>comes</hi> r. <hi>comers.</hi> p. 19. l. 1. for <hi>faireſt</hi> r. <hi>fair'ſt.</hi> l. 12. for <hi>beaury</hi> r. <hi>beauty.</hi> l. 25. for <hi>madſt</hi> r. <hi>made.</hi> p. 21. l. 2. for <hi>love</hi> r. <hi>low.</hi> l. 17. r. <hi>it.</hi> p. 13. in the marg. l. 19. for <hi>his</hi> r. <hi>her.</hi> p. 15. l. 5. in the marg. for <hi>refrain</hi> r. <hi>reſtrain.</hi> p. 25. l. 39. for <hi>treaſure</hi> r. <hi>treaſury.</hi> p. 28. l. 16. put in <hi>this heats,</hi> p. 31 l. 17. put in <hi>it.</hi> p. 32. l. 2. for <hi>maiſt</hi> r. <hi>muſt.</hi> p. 36. l. 16. for <hi>whether</hi> r. <hi>whither.</hi> l. 34. after <hi>purpoſes</hi> r. <hi>of ours.</hi> p. 38. l. 18. for <hi>ſingle</hi> r. <hi>ſinful.</hi> p. 39. l. 18. for <hi>ere</hi> r. <hi>art.</hi> p. 40. l. 20. for <hi>account</hi> r <hi>accounts.</hi> p. 43. l. 31. for <hi>ſatisfy</hi> r. <hi>teſtifie.</hi> p. 46. l. 5. for <hi>cleareſt</hi> r. <hi>clearer.</hi> p. 47. l. 29. for <hi>thee</hi> r. <hi>unto thee.</hi> l. 30. for <hi>from thee</hi> r. <hi>fro thee.</hi> p. 49. l. 2. for <hi>ſo</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> l. 22. for <hi>ſtops</hi> r. <hi>ſtoops.</hi> p. 50. l. 21. for <hi>God</hi> r. <hi>Gods.</hi> p. 52. l. 1. for <hi>divers</hi> r. <hi>drivers.</hi> l. 35. for <hi>bear</hi> r. <hi>bare.</hi> l. 39. for <hi>not</hi> r. <hi>out.</hi> p. 54. l. 13. for <hi>heavy</hi> r. <hi>hairy.</hi> l. 29. for <hi>do</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 57. l. 18. for <hi>from</hi> r. <hi>fro.</hi> p. 58. l. 4. for <hi>excell</hi> r. <hi>exceeds.</hi> p. 61. l. 4. for <hi>beſt.</hi> r. <hi>breſt.</hi> l. 19. for <hi>would</hi> r. <hi>could.</hi> l. 31. for <hi>of falſhood</hi> r. <hi>or falſhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo take notice, That whereas in many places on</hi> Jona <hi>there is no diſtinction between that part of the hiſtory, and what is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from it, therefore to avoid confuſion know, that where you finde it thus marked</hi> l—, <hi>there the Obſervation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and where it is again thus marked</hi> l— <hi>there it ends.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Song of Solomon" type="biblical_paraphrase">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:104634:5"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104634:5"/>
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>THe Song of Songs (moſt excellent)</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who by the guide</l>
                  <l>Of Gods ſpirit doth repreſent</l>
                  <l>Chriſt and his Church, the lovely bride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Saints do deſire to enjoy more ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes, ſeals and aſſurances of the love of Ieſus Chriſt.</note>Oh let him come and me embrace,</l>
                  <l>And with his mouth let him me kiſs,</l>
                  <l>For my ſoul's longing for the grace</l>
                  <l>That flows from that ſweet ſpirit of his:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">In adverſity and proſperity the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Chriſt is better then the choiceſt, chiefeſt of all things beſide</note>For why thy loves are better far</l>
                  <l>And night and day make me more glad,</l>
                  <l>Then all the choiceſt wines that are</l>
                  <l>Or were, or ever ſhall be had.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">The graces of Chriſt, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyntings of his holy ſpirit, are ſweet, precious, pure and powerful in working.</note>Thine oyntments Lord all of the beſt</l>
                  <l>Are ſweeter then the choyce perfume,</l>
                  <l>Their vertue heals the ſoul oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>That ſin &amp; Satan would conſume.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">His blood powred out and life ſpilt upon the croſs:</note>Thou waſt pour'd out like ointment pure</l>
                  <l>Thou emptied waſt, me for to fill;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">A fountain ſet open for ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs <hi>Zach. 13.1.</hi> a well of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpringing up to life everlaſting</note>Yet thou art full, and ſhalt endure</l>
                  <l>An overflowing fountain ſtill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">The love of Chriſt conſtrains ſouls to be obedient.</note>Thy grace diffus'd, the virgins move,</l>
                  <l>Thy love ſhed forth 's the only cauſe,</l>
                  <l>The pure in heart and life thee love,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">True love is made manifeſt, in keeping Chriſts precepts.</note>And loving thee they keep thy laws.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt ſenſible of her own and members nothingneſs, weakneſs, backwardneſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs, prays for aſſiſtance, and promiſes a good improvement.</note>Draw me and mine (to goodneſs ſlack)</l>
                  <l>Perſwad's to come to thee in haſt,</l>
                  <l>Put forth thy power when we draw back</l>
                  <l>We'l run and follow thee full faſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">There is a ſpecial intimacy between Chriſt and ſaints: he will ſhew them his ſecret, which angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to peep into, <hi>Pſal. 25.14.</hi>
                     </note>The Royall king, juſt, ſtrong, and wiſe</l>
                  <l>Not only outward kindneſs ſhews,</l>
                  <l>But all his chamber ſecreſies</l>
                  <l>To them that fear him he'l diſcloſe.</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104634:6"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Chriſt is the object of a Chriſtians joy: a divine contemplation of Chriſt, begets divine affection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt.</note>Much more then wine thy love we mind</l>
                  <l>With joy moſt pure it glads our heart,</l>
                  <l>More we think on thee more we finde,</l>
                  <l>Thou by the upright loved art.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">A ſenſibleneſs of deformity works deep humility, ingenious confeſſion.</note>I now deformed am, and black,</l>
                  <l>As black as <hi>kedars</hi> tents by name,</l>
                  <l>Afflictions great, and ſin (alack)</l>
                  <l>Hath brought me to confeſs the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">The ſaints are beautiful through grace; without ſpot through Chriſt, yet their glory is within.</note>Yet daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like to the curtains bright and fair,</l>
                  <l>Which once ſurrounded <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I comely am through Chriſt as they're.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">The Churches diſcoulorings laſt not always: 'tis but for a moment in wrath the Lord hides his face, therefore divide not, deſpiſe not enemies, diſpare not friends.</note>With evil eye behold me not,</l>
                  <l>Though beauty mine be turn'd to ſtain,</l>
                  <l>The ſuns hot beams hath caus'd this ſpot</l>
                  <l>And time will wipe it off again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Friends degenerate, do often if not always turn the moſt implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies.</note>My mothers children angry were</l>
                  <l>To keep the vinyards (when they ſtept</l>
                  <l>Aſide;) they made me (oh ſevere)</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">The Churches devaſtation gives cauſe of ſad complaint.</note>Therefore my vineyard is not kept.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">A fenſe of ignorance and weakneſs drives to Chriſt, for ſtrength and direction.</note>Oh tell me where thy flock doth feed</l>
                  <l>Thou whom my ſoul doth dearly love,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Chriſt is a Chriſtians ſweeteſt ſhade in the hotteſt perſecution.</note>Where they lie down i'th days of dread</l>
                  <l>When ſcorching heat their faith doth prove.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Chriſts ſheep are careful to follow him <hi>John 10.</hi> and fearful of falſe teachers and corrupt and falſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</note>For fear leſt I ſhould go aſtray,</l>
                  <l>After the flocks (to turn aſide)</l>
                  <l>Of thy companions in the way</l>
                  <l>Thy faithful followers never try'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">They that abaſe themſelves ſhall be exalted and they that ask ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive directions, <hi>Mat. 7.7.</hi>
                     </note>If thou know not that art ſo fair</l>
                  <l>My word and ſpirit ſhall thee guide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">New converts are as meek lambs <hi>Joh. 10.</hi> gathered into flocks, muſt keep from thoſe folds Chriſt hath not appointed.</note>Thy tender kids them take with care,</l>
                  <l>And feed the ſhepherds tents beſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">We muſt follow the faith and good works of thoſe before us, and make their pattern our example.</note>Go thy way forth, get out with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>From all falſe ways and worſhips go,</l>
                  <l>To th' footſteps of the flock take heed,</l>
                  <l>Conform thy ways, their ways unto.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104634:6"/>
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is orderly powerful and ſpeedy in executing the good pleaſure of Chriſt her head.</note>Much like to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> chariot horſes</l>
                  <l>My love, my dear, I thee compare</l>
                  <l>Who goodly are, and keep their courſes</l>
                  <l>Through me thou'rt as choice as they are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">A converſation becoming the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is the Churches duty and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beauty <hi>Phi. 1.19. 1 Pet. 3.3, 4.</hi>
                     </note>Thy cheeks with jewels thou doſt deck</l>
                  <l>A ſight moſt comely to behold,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">The Church obſerving Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, is not enthrald thereby, but in glorious freedome.</note>And thou haſt round about thy neck</l>
                  <l>Chains, that are wrought of pureſt gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">The three and yet but one, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd by promiſe to make the Church very glorious through divers preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpiritual Goſpel endowments.</note>Both father, ſon, and holy Ghoſt</l>
                  <l>Will make for thee borders of gold,</l>
                  <l>With ſtuds of ſilver; things that moſt</l>
                  <l>Will make thee glorious to behold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">True grace is not idle, cannot be hid but is powr'd out like the ſweeteſt perfume or moſt pretious oyntment; in our ſolemn approaches to God; to the pleaſing of him greatly: and the good and benefit of our brethren.</note>That I may pleaſe the King full well</l>
                  <l>When at his table he ſits there,</l>
                  <l>My ſpiknard ſhall ſend ſorth its ſmell</l>
                  <l>In love, in mercy, praiſe and prayer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>My welbeloved is to me</l>
                  <l>(For mine he is, and one we are)</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Nothing can be more ſweet then Chriſt to that ſoul that once taſted how gracious the Lord is.</note>More ſweet then bags of mirrh can be</l>
                  <l>Or precious gums or things moſt rare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">The greateſt troubles worſt of times and things, cannot draw a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans love from Chriſt, but ſtill in his heart he hath his lodging place.</note>In darkſome night, in time of fear</l>
                  <l>When others leave him, yet will <hi>I</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twixt my breſts lay him, becauſe there</l>
                  <l>Within my breſt he loves to lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">The fruit received from Chriſt as redeemer is both abundant and full; durable, and laſting.</note>Much like the cluſtring camphire-tree</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Engedi</hi> her vineyards grows,</l>
                  <l>My welbeloved's ſuch to me</l>
                  <l>Vertue from that more from him flows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">A Christians holineſs is his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt comlineſs, and Chriſt doth ever praiſe and delight in that grace which himſelf beſtows.</note>Th'art fair my love thy comelineſs</l>
                  <l>Doth far exceed the brighteſt day,</l>
                  <l>Doves eyes thou haſt: not wantonneſs</l>
                  <l>But chaſtity they do bewray:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">A ſoul enriched decked and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with grace from Chriſt cannot but be affected with praiſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, who is the fountain and welſpring of all grace.</note>Behold beloved thou art fair</l>
                  <l>Yea and moſt pleaſant to be ſeen</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104634:7"/>
                  <l>With thine no beauty may compare</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Where Chriſt can joyns in ſpiritual union great increaſe follows thereon.</note> Alſo our fruitful bed is green.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt which is the houſe of the living God is both firm and ſtable, built upon the rock: and cannot be moved to decay.</note>Our glorious houſe is very ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>The beams thereof ſweet Cedar tree</l>
                  <l>The rafters firr: both laſting long</l>
                  <l>And ſtand it ſhall, though ſhaken be.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter II.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>I<note n="k" place="margin">Chriſt deſcribes his glorious excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lency, which the worldling deſpiſes, but is owned and honoured by the godly.</note> Am the roſe in <hi>Sharon</hi> grows,</l>
                  <l>Decking each heart that doth me wear</l>
                  <l>And lilly white, pure ſweet and bright</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">The heart of the humble and lowly perſon is a fit habitation for Chriſt.</note>In loweſt valleys am found there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">The way to heaven is a thorny way: ſin affliction and wicked men are always as thorns in the ſides of the godly.</note>As lillys fair, when found they are</l>
                  <l>Among the thorns by thorns are rent:</l>
                  <l>Yet them exceeds as lillys weeds,</l>
                  <l>In beauty, bravery, ſweetneſs, ſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So my love ſhe: muſt galled be</l>
                  <l>With vexing thorns which her ſurround,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">The ſpouſe and true Church of Chriſt excels all other aſſemblies in grace here; and ſhall exceed them in glory hereafter.</note>Yet ſhe's alone: and like her none</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the daughters can be found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Nor angels nor men comparable to Chriſt, he is the only one that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes all other.</note>Him <hi>I</hi> love beſt, excels the reſt</l>
                  <l>Of all the ſons; though ne're ſo good,</l>
                  <l>As apples do; the fruits that grow</l>
                  <l>Upon the wild trees of the wood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Chriſt is a Chriſtians ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, when most weary and heavy loaden.</note>When <hi>I</hi> am ſpent: what great content</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> take to ſit me down and reſt,</l>
                  <l>Under the ſhade, which he hath made</l>
                  <l>For weary ſouls, and ſore oppreſt:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Every true believer by a living faith doth pluck from this tree of life both remiſſion of ſin, ſanctifying grace, inward peace, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the holy Ghost flow in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</note>How various are the fruits ſo rare</l>
                  <l>That on this living tree ſtill grows?</l>
                  <l>Their vertu's much; there is none ſuch,</l>
                  <l>The ſweetneſs he that taſteth knows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104634:7"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Christ in and through his holy ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointments affords gracious ſouls ſweet refreſhment, thereby filling the heart of every true believer with joy and comfort.</note>He did me leade my foul to feed</l>
                  <l>With his fine dainties, choice and rare</l>
                  <l>Into the place: of ſweeteſt grace</l>
                  <l>Where pureſt joys and comforts are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Chriſt doth guide preſerve and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all his ſervants in what he requires at their hands, though they meet with never ſo many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in the performance.</note>For to protect: and me direct</l>
                  <l>His banner o're me is diſplay'd</l>
                  <l>When ſtrength abates it animates,</l>
                  <l>None fighting under it are diſmayd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">The comforts of Chriſt are full, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying, and yield the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to the thirſty ſoul, broken in heart, and languiſhing ſpirit.</note>Let thy comforts be my ſupports,</l>
                  <l>With flagons full me overflow,</l>
                  <l>With apples ſtay me from decay,</l>
                  <l>That on the tree of life do grow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">The glorious excellencies, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent beauty, and unparallel'd love of Chriſt, doth ſo deeply ſtrike and wound the heart of a Chriſtian, that nothing can cure it but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment and poſſeſſion of Chriſt himſelf.</note>Why, there is need, my heart doth bleed</l>
                  <l>Thy love it gave my heart the wound,</l>
                  <l>And wounded <hi>I</hi> love-ſick do lie,</l>
                  <l>To cure me none els can be found:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">The dear embraces of Chriſt, his vehement affection and almighty power is the preſervation and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſouls, when ſinking, or falen into the loweſt ſtate.</note>His left hand's layd under my head,</l>
                  <l>To bear it up each day and hour;</l>
                  <l>And he doth cover me all over,</l>
                  <l>With his right hand of love and power:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Each gracious ſoul will be very careful of diſpleaſing Chriſt, and uſe all lawfal means to prevent the ſins of others and ſtir them up to their duty.</note>Church members all; both great &amp; ſmal</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> charge you (as you'l anſwer me)</l>
                  <l>By roes and hindes: or any kindes</l>
                  <l>Of things beſides, that lovely be;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That my dear love ye do not move,</l>
                  <l>Provoke, ſtir up, nor's ſpirit greive</l>
                  <l>By evil ways: nor till he pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Awake him not but ſtill believe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Chriſts ſheep know his voice from a ſtrangers, they hear and follow him.</note>Lo he appears: my ſoul now hears</l>
                  <l>The voice of my beloved one,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">When Chriſt will ſave his people and deſtroy his and their enemies, he will be both ſpeedy therein and ſucceſsful.</note>Loe he doth come my foes to doom,</l>
                  <l>And judge them to perdition.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He leaps in haſt: and skips full faſt</l>
                  <l>Ore hills and mountains in his way</l>
                  <l>When he will ſave: no let he'l have</l>
                  <l>Nor enemy to make him ſtay:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104634:8"/>
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">The Lord Chriſt is both ready and preſent in time of trouble.</note>No roe can be more ſwift then he,</l>
                  <l>No hart though young can run ſo faſt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">He wayes to be gracious.</note>He ſtands and calls behind our ſtalls</l>
                  <l>Knocking to let him in at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">And takes a ſtrict ſurvey of all things done whether good or evil.</note>Oh do not ſin: for he looks in</l>
                  <l>As at a window he eſpies</l>
                  <l>What we are doing, while he is ſhewing</l>
                  <l>Himſelf ſo plain to open eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">The beſt of Saints have an aptneſs to and ſomtimes are found upon the bed of ſecurity.</note>My beſt belov'd, with mercy mov'd</l>
                  <l>Seeing me ſluggiſh and ſecure,</l>
                  <l>And in my minde to ſin inclin'd</l>
                  <l>(A thing his grace cannot endure);</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">The voyce of Chriſt, and his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous call doth ſtrongly move a ſleepy ſoul to ariſe from ſinful reſt to have communion with himſelf.</note>He calls and crys to me, ariſe</l>
                  <l>My love my fair one come away,</l>
                  <l>Forſake thy reſt: vain things deteſt,</l>
                  <l>Make haſt and have no longer ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">No affliction nor preſecution ſhould keep from Chriſt for they are but for a moment, of no continuance.</note>The winters blaſt is gone and paſt,</l>
                  <l>Tempeſtuous ſtorms no more ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Gods wrathful ſhours no more he pours</l>
                  <l>On freinds but on his enemies:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">The hearts of men are like barren earth, till planted by the ſpirit, and ſown with grace, then they are fruitful.</note>the flowrs appear ſhew ſummer's near</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">There is a time to mourn &amp; a time to rejoyce, Saints know it, and in due ſeaſon warble forth Gods praiſes.</note>Each chirping bird doth fit and ſing,</l>
                  <l>The turtles voice doth make a noiſe,</l>
                  <l>All which beſpeak a glorious ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>The figtree puts forth her green ſhoots,</l>
                  <l>Her unripe figs are ſweetned well</l>
                  <l>The vines alſo do dangling grow</l>
                  <l>With graps that give forth a good ſmell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Each token ſays that ſummer days,</l>
                  <l>Are haſting on without delay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">though men be unwilling to come, yet Chriſt is not weary to call to them over and over by many moving ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to come to him.</note>Wherefore ariſe: from worldly toys</l>
                  <l>My love my fair one come away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Chriſts ſpouſe is both harmleſs, and pure neither without preſecution, nor then without a hiding place in God.</note>Now oh my dove, what can thee move</l>
                  <l>Sith thou art in the ſecret ſtairs,</l>
                  <l>And rocky clifts: free from the drifts</l>
                  <l>And ſtorms of foes, and other fears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104634:8"/>
                  <l>The barb'rous foes do thee incloſe,</l>
                  <l>And thou lyeſt hid in ſecret place</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Faith &amp; prayer the beſt practiſe, &amp; very requiſite in time of affliction.</note>Yet let me hear thy voyce in prayer:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Good works joyned with prayer and a converſation becoming the Goſpel is acceptable to, (and lovely in the eye of) the Lord Jeſus.</note>And ſee the beauty of thy face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For there's no creature hath a feature</l>
                  <l>Like thine, ſo comely to behold</l>
                  <l>Thy praying voice: it hath a noiſe</l>
                  <l>More ſweet, then by words can be told.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Thoſe that hurt the Church by fraud or force, doctrine or manners, ought to be reproved, puniſhed.</note>The foxes take: that ſpoyl do make</l>
                  <l>Upon our vines: for every tree</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">The weak and infirm in Chriſts Church muſt be cared for, for they are equal with others in his love and Favour.</note>Young grapes do bear: and with great care</l>
                  <l>Such tender plants preſerv'd muſt be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Every true Chriſtian is given up wholy to Chriſt, and by faith makes Chriſt his own.</note>Mine my love is: and I am his</l>
                  <l>My all on him I will beſtow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Chriſt is much delighted, with the ſweet and beautifying graces of his people.</note>He reſts and feeds: not among weeds</l>
                  <l>But where the pureſt lillys grow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Till Chriſt the ſun of glory, break in upon a ſoul it ſits in darkneſs and ſhadows of death.</note>Whilſt it is night: and till the light</l>
                  <l>Of day do break, &amp; it grow clear</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſhady clowds, the brightneſs ſhrouds</l>
                  <l>Till they diſperſe and thou appear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">The true Church begs Chriſts ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſpecial preſence to ſupport her under all her preſſures, and to put an end to all differences.</note>Be like a roe, young hart or doe</l>
                  <l>On mountains where diviſions are,</l>
                  <l>Turn deareſt one, and be thou known</l>
                  <l>Of me to take a ſpecial care.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Carnal ſecurity will give Chriſt cauſe to withdraw and hide himſelf.</note>WHen I had loſt the preſent ſight</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">True love is always working and puts thee upon to ſeek for Chriſt when withdrawn.</note>Of him whom my ſoul loveth beſt</l>
                  <l>I ſought him in the darkſom night</l>
                  <l>His abſence gave me ſuch unreſt.</l>
                  <l>I ſought him, and muſt ſeek him ſtill</l>
                  <l>be found at firſt he ſeldome will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104634:9"/>
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">That ſoul that makes Chriſt her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, will riſe and rouze up to ſeek him without delay.</note>I will ariſe up from my eaſe</l>
                  <l>And ſeek my love in every ſtreet,<note n="w" place="margin">Falne Chriſtians are not eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd, and thoſe that do deſert Chriſt do not quickly ſee the light of his countenance ſhining upon them.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Chriſt is not always found in thoſe places that men ſeek him in, yet muſt we not leave to ſeek him in any of his appointments.</note>From thence I'le paſs to the broadways</l>
                  <l>To ſeek him where the aſſemblies meet.</l>
                  <l>I ſought him there, to pleaſe my mind</l>
                  <l>But ſeeking there, him could not finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Thus reſtleſs I ſtill wandring was</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Sometimes gratious ſouls wanting Chriſt do enquire for him of thoſe that know not how to direct to him.</note>Till by the watchmen I was found,</l>
                  <l>As they along the City paſs</l>
                  <l>Tending their watch walking the round,</l>
                  <l>To whom I ſaid, (for grace did move)</l>
                  <l>Saw ye him whom my ſoul doth love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">We muſt leave men and their devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and wayt upon the Lord in his own ways, and he will ſoon diſcover &amp; manifeſt himſelf gratious to us.</note>No anſwer good they gave to me</l>
                  <l>Direction from them I had none</l>
                  <l>How my ſoul ſatisfi'd ſhould be</l>
                  <l>But when I left them, and was gone</l>
                  <l>Away from them a little time,</l>
                  <l>I found him that was wholly mine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">We muſt hold what we have of Chriſt, ſtand faſt in that liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free.</note>When I of him faſt hold had caught,</l>
                  <l>Again I would not let him go,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">A Chriſtian deſires to enjoy Chriſt in the inner man moſtly: and to ſee his goings in his ſanctuary alſo.</note>Till my late-found dear love was brought</l>
                  <l>My mothers dwelling houſe into,</l>
                  <l>And till my ſouls moſt ſecret place</l>
                  <l>Were lodging chambers for his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Every true Chriſtian hath a care leſt he ſhould offend Chriſt, and will uſe his beſt endeavour that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo do neither provoke nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſe him.</note>Ye daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I charge you have a ſpecial care,</l>
                  <l>(By roes and hindes and each of them</l>
                  <l>Or other things that lovely are)</l>
                  <l>That ye wake not by wicked ways</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtir my love untill he pleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Thoſe ſouls delivered from a loſt and bewilder'd eſtate by Chriſt their redeemer, muſt needs riſe up heaven-ward in fervency of ſpirit and dear affection.</note>What glorious one, oh who is this</l>
                  <l>Like ſmoaky pillars doth aſcend</l>
                  <l>Out of the deſart wilderneſs</l>
                  <l>Sure 'tis my love, my dove, my freind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">The prayers praiſes and all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſacrifices of Saints are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſweet when perfumed by the interceſſion of Chriſt the mediator.</note>Who's all perſumd (as it is meet)</l>
                  <l>With mirrh and frankincenſe ſo ſweet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104634:9"/>
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Each true believer beds his beloved in his boſome which is Chriſt Jeſus.</note>Behold the bed, that bed of his</l>
                  <l>The great and mighty <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Each gratious heart a lodging is</l>
                  <l>For him to take his reſt upon,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">A Chriſtians priviledge is to be kept by Chriſt, and he as a good ſouldier doth reſiſt the adverſary.</note>There valiant <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and ſtout</l>
                  <l>Compaſs this princely bed about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Gods people have many enemies to withſtand are always in danger to be ſurpriz'd, and therefore have need of skilfulneſs and courage.</note>As valiant ſo they many are</l>
                  <l>They all hold ſwords within their hand,</l>
                  <l>Skilful likewiſe expect in warr</l>
                  <l>Their enemies for to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Each hath his ſword on's thigh out-right</l>
                  <l>Becauſe of terrors in the night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>The Chariot which king <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did make was glorious to behold,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt excels in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at the preſent, through Chriſts righteouſneſs and a life without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and blame in the world, they have a right to all now, for all is theirs, and ſhall be ſet in full and actuall poſſeſſion hereafter of all thoſe good things, which God hath layd up in ſtore for them that love him.</note>The wood the choice in <hi>Lebanon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Silver were pillars, and pure Gold</l>
                  <l>Did bottom it, things of great worth</l>
                  <l>The Churches glory to let ſorth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A purple veil of crimſon red</l>
                  <l>(Such bloody veils do hide our ſin)</l>
                  <l>Was for a covering o're it ſpread,</l>
                  <l>And flames of love pave it within;</l>
                  <l>This is ordain'd only for them</l>
                  <l>The daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">The faithful are cal'd out of ſin, ſelf and world, that ſo they may have the full enjoyment of Jeſus Chriſt.</note>O <hi>Sions</hi> daughters go ye forth</l>
                  <l>Leave ſin and carnal vanities</l>
                  <l>And ſee the king of precious worth</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſight will fill and glad your eyes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Every gracious ſoul will put the crown upon the head of Chriſt, by a willing ſubjection unto him, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering him to reign and rule over him, ſubduing his luſts, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing all that is at enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt within him.</note>Behold the king of great renown</l>
                  <l>Hath on his head his glorious crown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">True believers are Chriſts mother and dear relations, their holy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it is their glory and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Goſpel, ſo it is as a crown put upon the head of Chriſt.</note>Who by his mother crowned was</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">When ſouls are ſpiritually conjoynd to Chriſt, and eſpous'd by faith and obedience, great are heavenly joys at that eſpouſal.</note>On his heart-gladding marriage day</l>
                  <l>Now all his foes cry out alas</l>
                  <l>But ſing ye friends that him obey;</l>
                  <l>For with the ſcepter of his power</l>
                  <l>His, and your foes he will devour.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104634:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>BEhold th'art fair my love behold th'art fair</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is knowing, chaſt, comely and pure, and ſo keeps her ſelf that he may delight and take pleaſure in her.</note>Doves eyes thou haſt lye veil'd within thy locks</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Saints graces within, where lyes moſt of their ſtrength, and a holy well order'd comely converſation without makes them ſhine in the eyes of all beholders.</note>And to compleat thy beauty, thou haſt hair</l>
                  <l>Reſembles well the ſmooth and gliſtring flocks</l>
                  <l>Of goats, that from <hi>mount-gilead</hi> do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear</l>
                  <l>And grazing in due order are found there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Thy teeth the inſtruments, (which food prepare)</l>
                  <l>Are like a flock of ſheep, new clipt and ſhorn</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Chriſts flocks or followers are fruitful, his branches bearing, ſterrility and barrenneſs inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with that ſpirit that makes them grow and increaſe in all the increaſings of God.</note>As they from waſhing come, white clean they are</l>
                  <l>And purg'd from filthineſs, thee to adorn</l>
                  <l>With glorious beauty, and amongſt them there</l>
                  <l>None barren is, but each one twins doth bear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Our ſervices done to God, are all acceptable, perfect and compleat, through the blood of Chriſt.</note>Like to twiſted threed of Scarlet red</l>
                  <l>Such are thy lips; the portalls of thy prayers</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Gracious ſpeeches and words is comely for Chriſtians, a holy lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is their ornament, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers edification.</note>And praiſes too, thy ſpeech is garniſhed</l>
                  <l>With grace and ſweetneſs, fitting gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ears;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">It is required of Chriſtians, and it is the property of all truly ſuch to be humble, chaſte and modeſt.</note>Thy bluſhing temples hid with hairy fleeces</l>
                  <l>Like a pomegranate are, when cut in pieces:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">That Chriſtian that draws life from Chriſt by faith, ſtands ſtifly againſt all oppoſition, conquers all comes, latches every fiery dart of the devil, ſubmits to Chriſts will and perſeveres in his ways.</note>Thy neck the glorious embleme of thy power</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104634:10"/>
                  <l>Is ſtretched out to each beholders eye</l>
                  <l>Reſembling well the high and lofty tower</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>David,</hi> builded for an armoury</l>
                  <l>Whereon a thouſand bucklers fixed are</l>
                  <l>All <hi>ſhields</hi> of mighty men prepard for <hi>war</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt hath within her ſelf like a tender mother both feeders and feeding, both pure and wholſome, to nouriſh and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, all that are born in her.</note>Like to the twins of young and tender roes</l>
                  <l>Which among lillies feed &amp; take repaſt</l>
                  <l>Not among filthy weeds, ſure like to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Are thy two holy breaſts, wherewith thou haſt</l>
                  <l>Nouriſht thy children, like a tender mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</l>
                  <l>That they in ſtrength of grace excell all other.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Chriſtians, till the everlaſting day ſwalow up their darkneſs muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect bitter as well as ſweet, through many tribulations they muſt enter in the kingdom of God.</note>Now will I get me to the mountain high</l>
                  <l>Of bitter mirrh, and hills of frankincenſe</l>
                  <l>Till break of day and till the morning sky</l>
                  <l>Expell the dark and ſhady clouds from thence;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Chriſt will never leave nor forſake his in their forlorne ſtate, but will protect them, preſerve them, provide for them untill he bring them to glory.</note>There ſhall my gracious preſence thee attend</l>
                  <l>Until thy ſorrows in ſweet joy ſhall end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Juſtification by faith hides all ſin, we are beautiful in him who is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beauty, holy, beloved and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and through him who is holyneſſe, love, and accepted of the father.</note>Nothing offenſive no imperfect ſtain</l>
                  <l>My eye ſees on thee (though ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply are)</l>
                  <l>My righteous covering always ſtands between</l>
                  <l>Thy worſt and me therefore I do declare</l>
                  <l>Thou art all fair my love and there is not</l>
                  <l>A blemiſh found on thee, nor any ſpot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Chriſtians when cal'd to have communion with Chriſt willingly leave their greateſt, goodlieſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honours, profits, pleaſures for Chriſt, and in looſing all with and for him do gain much.</note>Now come with me from <hi>Lebanon</hi> my ſpouſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amana, Hermon, Shenirs</hi> hils refrain,</l>
                  <l>For they that follow me can never looſe</l>
                  <l>But in their loſſes wil be found their gain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">He that walks with Chriſt hath his filthineſs clenſed, his Lyon-like cruel nature changed, neither will he have any more fellowſhip with the workers in (or works of) dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>From th' Lyons dens and Leopards mountains flee</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104634:11"/>
                  <l>With ſin, and ſinful bruits, canſt thou agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">The grace of the holy ſpirit work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing powerfully in and upon the hearts of Gods people carrying them out to a holy ſubmiſſion to Chriſts will and obedience to his commands doth beget in Chriſt unſpeakable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraled affection.</note>My ſiſter ſpouſe, oh what great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</l>
                  <l>Hath thy eye on me like a piercing dart,</l>
                  <l>Thy faith or love, or both hath taken hence</l>
                  <l>From me to thee my raviſht vanquiſht heart,</l>
                  <l>Beſides, the chaines that have thy neck ſurrounded</l>
                  <l>Makes me complain my heart with love is wounded.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Chriſt doth extoll and magnify the ſpirituall beauty of his Church, and her love to him is more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the choiceſt of things.</note>My ſiſter ſpouſe thy love is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous fair</l>
                  <l>And in my eye beyond all imitation</l>
                  <l>The choiceſt wines, that ever were or are</l>
                  <l>Like thy love are not in my eſtimation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Saints have received of the anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the father, who by diffuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into all actions ſpiritual &amp; civil makes them have a fragrant and ſweet ſavour every where.</note>Thy oyntments ſmells ſo odoriferous,</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt ſpice is not ſo ſweet as thoſe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">The words of the Lord in the mouths of his ſervants, are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pure, precious, and ſweet in themſelves, but alſo pleaſing to God and profitable to them that receive them.</note>Thy lips drop like an honey combe my ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>Each open eare thy gracious words are filling</l>
                  <l>Beneath thy tongue honey and milke it flows</l>
                  <l>Much like a fountain pleaſantly diſtiling.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Chriſts righteouſneſs is the ſaints rayment, and ſpiritual clothing, who by faith puts it on, is of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable redolency, admirable ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>The garments pure that I have put thee on</l>
                  <l>Smels ſweeter then the ſcent of <hi>Labanon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruitfull, and delectable, beſet with enemies on each ſide, yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſt with the power and preſence of Chriſt, ſo that they cannot waſte nor ſpoyle it.</note>Thou art a garden both for fruit and flower</l>
                  <l>My ſiſter ſpouſe a garden well inclos'd</l>
                  <l>And fenc'd with walls of my almighty power</l>
                  <l>T'keep thee from foes, to which thou art expos'd.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104634:11"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">In the Church of Chriſt there doth always riſe up a freſh-ſpring of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life and grace from Chriſt the head, to water and refreſh it.</note>A ſpring ſhut up a fountain ſealed, caſting</l>
                  <l>Up waters in thee to life everlaſting.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">Thoſe plants ſet by Chriſt, fenc'd by his power, and watered by his grace, cannot be barren but bring forth much fruit, by which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is glorifyed here, and they with the father and ſon glorifyed hereafter.</note>Thy plants an orchard of pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats are</l>
                  <l>Thy branches are a paradice of pleaſure</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of fruits moſt excellent and rare</l>
                  <l>Are found in thee without compare and meaſure.</l>
                  <l>Camphire with ſpiknard, oh what fruits are growing</l>
                  <l>There where my grace is always over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Chriſt out of his fulneſs, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate freely, abundantly, and in divers kinds, his graces, to his Church, ſo that nothing can be wanting for his edification and comfort.</note>There's ſpikenard ſweet and cordiall ſaffron too</l>
                  <l>Mirh, aloes, calamus and cinamon,</l>
                  <l>All trees of frankincenſe in it do grow</l>
                  <l>Each thing it hath a precious operation;</l>
                  <l>Her ſpices choice for vertue &amp; for worth</l>
                  <l>Nor man nor angels tongue can ſet them forth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>A garden full of fountains, precious pure,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Chriſt the living fountain ſet open for ſin and uncleanneſs, is to be found in his Church, with grace in abundance, ready and willing to ſupply, ſuccour, ſupport and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort every ſoul that waits for him.</note>A well of living waters ſpringing ſtill</l>
                  <l>Each ſinful ſickly ſilthy ſoul to cure</l>
                  <l>And all are cal'd to waſh and drink that will:</l>
                  <l>And as the ſtreams do flow from <hi>Lebanon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So flows all ſtreams of grace from Chriſt alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">A gracious ſoul doth earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and much long after the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful workings of the ſpirit of Chriſt, producing its divers, yet all glorious effects in the ſoul.</note>Breath holy ſpirit on my garden now</l>
                  <l>That every ſpicy flower may bloome and ſpread</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Nor will expect ſolid ſound comfort before ſome Goſpel breakings, and ſpiritual caſtings down.</note>For as the north-wind thou mak'ſt me to bow</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104634:12"/>
                  <l>And with thy ſouthern gales lifts up my head</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">From Chriſt we have all, of his fulneſs we receive, we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore return him his own, for it is not ours or that from as, but his own, and that which proceeds from himſelf that is acceptable to him.</note>Come my beloved I have thee invited</l>
                  <l>And eat the fruit in which thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">The prayers of ſaints are very prevailing, Chriſt is prone and ready to hear; no ſooner can we call but we have our anſwer.</note>NOw I am come my ſpouſe</l>
                  <l>Into my garden gay</l>
                  <l>Thy call it did me rouſe</l>
                  <l>I hear when thou doſt pray;</l>
                  <l>It doth ſuffice</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Chriſt doth inable and impower his people to labour and bring forth pious, pure, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruits of faith, love, holyneſſe; ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal and ſuffering for his ſake, all very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant unto him.</note>I gather'd have: that which I gave my mirrh with ſpice.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">No comb of wantingneſs, weaknes, imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in grace or dutys, can harm the ſaints while there is the honey of ſweet ſincerity and truth of grace to be found.</note>Oh with what great delight</l>
                  <l>My honey comb I eat</l>
                  <l>And feed my appetite</l>
                  <l>With ſucking honey ſweet.</l>
                  <l>And though the beſt</l>
                  <l>May fail, or fall: yet ſincere, all</l>
                  <l>Of them are bleſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">As wine and milk are to us, ſo the pure, holy, ſincere ſervices of ſaints are unto Chriſt.</note>My wine and milk together</l>
                  <l>Being my delightful fare</l>
                  <l>I took and drunk; for neither</l>
                  <l>Of them that <hi>I</hi> can ſpare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Chriſt prepares his table, ſets on his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual daintys, invites his friends; and feaſts their ſouls with his fat things in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</note>Sure 't none offends</l>
                  <l>That ye eat ſuch: with me drink much</l>
                  <l>That are my freinds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">A gracious ſoul is ever ſenſible of its ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and will ingenuouſly confeſs it.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſleep and ſlug; which makes</l>
                  <l>Me ſorely to complain,</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104634:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Findes an oppoſition between fleſh &amp; ſpirit the part regenerate and wakefull heart is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways working upward towards Chriſt; though luſt and the part unregenerate would refrain.</note>But yet my heart it wakes</l>
                  <l>Though luſt would it reſtrayn.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Chriſts ſheep both know and hear the voice of Chriſt which doth powerfully awaken and rouze up the ſloathful ſleepy ſoul.</note>His voyce doth move</l>
                  <l>Who knocks and ſays, clear thou my ways</l>
                  <l>My ſpotleſſe dove.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">When Chriſt begs and ſues for admiſſion he gives power to open, it is then the wiſdom and duty of every Chriſtian to let him in.</note>Oh let me enter in</l>
                  <l>And lodge within thy breaſt</l>
                  <l>Ingratitude's thy ſin</l>
                  <l>Receive me as thy gueſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">The more and greater things Chriſt hath ſuffred for us, the greater obligation lyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to love and ſerve him, and the greater is the ſin to refuſe and neglect him.</note>For my head's fill'd</l>
                  <l>With dews of wet, and vapours great</l>
                  <l>Cold night doth yeild.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Man is apt to frame vain excuſes, and caſt in ſmall obſtructions to prevent the kindly entertainment of Chriſt, though the chiefeſt of ten thouſand, and none ſo worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> am diſrobed quite,</l>
                  <l>And may not take the cold</l>
                  <l>My feet are waſhen white</l>
                  <l>If <hi>I</hi> riſe they'le be foulld;</l>
                  <l>I'le take my eaſe</l>
                  <l>Sad are the ſhifts: when fleſhly drifts</l>
                  <l>Are fleſh to pleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">When Chriſt puts forth his ſpiritual power, he breaks in ſunder the ſtrongeſt bars, ſets wide open the cloſeſt heart, and makes way that the king of glory may enter in.</note>My well-beloved put</l>
                  <l>His hand in at the door</l>
                  <l>And opened what <hi>I</hi> ſhut</l>
                  <l>That kept him out before.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">The more a ſoul feels and diſcerns Chriſt in his moſt inward workings, the more it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd with love to Chriſt, leſs love to ſelf, and greif for former failings.</note>(O rare effect)</l>
                  <l>My bowels move: for my dear love</l>
                  <l>And my neglect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Where there is true repentance, that ſoul is rouzd up from ſleepy ſecurity, and is found readily and graciouſly acting the thing that is good.</note>When <hi>I</hi> did riſe and ſtir</l>
                  <l>To open to my dear</l>
                  <l>My hands did drop with mirrh</l>
                  <l>That on the lock was there</l>
                  <l>who 'f grace partake</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſouls will never want en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor</l>
                  <l>When once awake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104634:13"/>
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Chriſt being ſlighted and neglected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws his ſpiritual preſence and ſo leaves a ſoul in darkneſs and miſery.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> opened now in huſte</l>
                  <l>It was no time to ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But now the time is paſt</l>
                  <l>My lover's gone away;</l>
                  <l>A juſt reward</l>
                  <l>For he that ſu'd: and beg'd and woo'd</l>
                  <l>Had no regard.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">A refuſing the ſweet and gracious words of Chriſt, when ſeriouſly conſidered will break the heart with ſorrow.</note>But when <hi>I</hi> heard him ſpeak</l>
                  <l>My ſoul did melt away</l>
                  <l>That heart with grief muſt break</l>
                  <l>That ever ſaid him nay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Thoſe that ſtop their ears when Chriſt calls unto them, they ſhall cry and call (yea his own dear ones for a time) and not be heard.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſought in vain</l>
                  <l>My prayers and crys, he ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys</l>
                  <l>To entertain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>The watchmen they are found</l>
                  <l>Of whom I look't for ayd</l>
                  <l>They ſmote me and my wound</l>
                  <l>By them was deeper made:</l>
                  <l>Each one of thoſe</l>
                  <l>That did pretend: to be my friend</l>
                  <l>are turn'd my foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Sinful ſecurity breaks the Churches ſtaves of beauty and bands; robs her both of her glory and defence, expoſes to great ſhame and miſery.</note>The keepers of the walls</l>
                  <l>They took my vail away,</l>
                  <l>What miſcheif them befalls</l>
                  <l>That err and go aſtray</l>
                  <l>Alack alack</l>
                  <l>How ſoon our fame, is turn'd to ſhame</l>
                  <l>When we draw back.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ſpiritual deſertions, there is want of conſolation, 'tis a mercy to have the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to pray for us, and our duty to call in for their help.</note>
                     <hi>Jerus'lems</hi> daughters ye</l>
                  <l>That loving be and kinde</l>
                  <l>Who ſeek in the right way</l>
                  <l>That you my love may finde;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">Love and zeal warm the heart, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the faithful are fervent, and ſo avail much.</note>I charge ye when</l>
                  <l>Your hearts deſire, aſcends in fire</l>
                  <l>To minde me then.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:104634:13"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">A gracious ſoul languiſhing in love to Chriſt, grieves for former neglect, longs to be ſenſible of reconciliation to Chriſt, calls and cries to the faithful to preſent in prayer its ſad condition to him.</note>Oh tell him be ye ſure</l>
                  <l>That I am ſick of love</l>
                  <l>My heart cannot endure</l>
                  <l>Unleſs his bowels move;</l>
                  <l>For though I were</l>
                  <l>To ſlumber bent, and negligent</l>
                  <l>My heart's ſincere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">The more a Chriſtian knows of Chriſt the more he deſires and longs to know him, and therefore enquires of thoſe that have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience what beauty, lovelineſs, excellency, glory, and worth, they ſee. know and have found to be in him.</note>Why what is thy belov'd</l>
                  <l>More then another is</l>
                  <l>That thou ſo much art mov'd</l>
                  <l>For this abſence of his?</l>
                  <l>Why doſt ſo charge?</l>
                  <l>Is he of worth, then ſet thou forth</l>
                  <l>His praiſe at large.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Thoſe that are affected with Chriſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual glory; and have taſted the ſweetneſs that is in him; are fitteſt to deſcribe it to others, and will fully and freely communicate what they know, feel and are affected with; that others may love and admire him as themſelves.</note>My wel-beloved then</l>
                  <l>Which raviſht hath my heart</l>
                  <l>Chief of ten thouſand men</l>
                  <l>Is glorious in each part;</l>
                  <l>A mixture fine</l>
                  <l>Of red and white, to breed delite</l>
                  <l>In him doth ſhine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>His head whereon he wears</l>
                  <l>And's gliſtering crown doth hold</l>
                  <l>In glory it appears</l>
                  <l>Much like the fineſt gold:</l>
                  <l>His locks together</l>
                  <l>Are buſhy ſet: as black as jet</l>
                  <l>Or ravens feather.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Chriſt is meek, humble, holy, perfectly pure, who cannot look on ſin with the leaſt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, teaching us hereby, that as he is ſo ſhould we be in this world.</note>As are the eyes of doves</l>
                  <l>In ſprings that take delight</l>
                  <l>So are his eyes who loves</l>
                  <l>No evil in his ſight;</l>
                  <l>His gentle eyes</l>
                  <l>With milk are wet: and even ſet</l>
                  <l>Impartiall-wife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104634:14"/>
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">The face of Chriſt is tranſcendantly comly, bleſt are all ſuch who live in the light of his countenance, and whoſe ſouls are ſweetned and delighted with his preſence.</note>His cheeks much like the bowers</l>
                  <l>Or beds of ſpices are</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt of all flowers</l>
                  <l>With his may not compare;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">The words of Chriſt have a diſtaſtful reliſh to the miſled ſinner, but to the obedient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever are pure &amp; precious, being hid in his heart, preſerves it from all rottenneſs, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſin and filth whatſoever.</note>His lips diſtills</l>
                  <l>Sweet ſmelling mirh: ſure none can err</l>
                  <l>Whoſe heart it fills.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Chriſt is alway ready abundantly to ſupply the wants of his people, and to help them by his power in time of need.</note>His hands like to gold rings</l>
                  <l>Set with a precious ſtone</l>
                  <l>The choyceſt of good things</l>
                  <l>He freely gives his own:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Chriſts Compaſſions are great to all, and his heart is moſt affectionately ſet upon his own humble and holy ones.</note>His belly much</l>
                  <l>Like ivory bright: with ſaphirs dight</l>
                  <l>And heart is ſuch.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Chriſt by his almighty power hath overcome and vanquiſht all for the good and ſakes of his, and they ſhall vanquiſh and overcome all that oppoſes them by the ſame power of the Lord Jeſus.</note>His legs his feet and thighs</l>
                  <l>Like marble pillars are,</l>
                  <l>Whereon ſuch ſtrength there lies</l>
                  <l>None may with it compare;</l>
                  <l>And more behold,</l>
                  <l>His feet are ſet: in ſockets neat</l>
                  <l>Of fineſt gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">The ſpiritual glory of Chriſt ſurpaſſes all glory; beheld only by thoſe whoſe eyes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to look into thoſe abſtruſe and hidden things of the Goſpel.</note>His countenance whereon</l>
                  <l>To look doth dim the eye</l>
                  <l>Is like to lebanon</l>
                  <l>Sweet, glorious, comely, high.</l>
                  <l>It doth excell</l>
                  <l>The cedars tall: and alſo all</l>
                  <l>That tongue can tell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Every word proceeding from the mouth of Chriſt was a word of grace peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and ſweeter then the honey comb.</note>Moſt gracious are his words</l>
                  <l>That from his mouth diſtils,</l>
                  <l>Great comfort it affords</l>
                  <l>Each gracious heart it fils.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Chriſt in every part abſolutly perfect, or the rare and excellent perfection of Chriſt, is all that a gracious ſoul can deſire, raviſhing the heart of a true believer.</note>my whole deſires</l>
                  <l>He is alone: and there is none</l>
                  <l>My heart ſo fires.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104634:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">A powerful and plain deſcription of Chriſt drawn out to the life in truth and reallity is of great effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or Chriſt powerfully preacht to the hearts and conſciences of men is of great force to draw them out to enquire and ſeek after him.</note>WHere is he gone, faireſt of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</l>
                  <l>Where's thy beloved turn'd aſide</l>
                  <l>Do not deny, our company</l>
                  <l>In ſeeking him who is our guide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Thoſe that have found Chriſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are very free and willing to inſtruct thoſe that are deſirous to ſeek after him.</note>My dear love he, is gone to ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Chriſt is much delighted in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian aſſemblies, where their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are holy, their ſervices are ſweet and ſpicy.</note>The gardens where he doth delight</l>
                  <l>And much rejoyce, i'th beds of ſpice</l>
                  <l>And gathering the lillies white.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Every true Chriſtian is reſign'd and wholy given up to Chriſt, by faith makes Chriſt his own with all his benefits.</note>Mine my love is: and I am his</l>
                  <l>(What comfort from this union flows)</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">The Lord Chriſt takes great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the ſweet pure and lovely graces which he himſelf beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people.</note>He reſts and feeds: not among weeds</l>
                  <l>But where the pureſt lillys grows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Great is the glory riches &amp; honour of the Church of Jeſus Chriſt.</note>Thy beaury bright: is like (in ſight)</l>
                  <l>To royal <hi>Tirzah</hi> of great fame</l>
                  <l>Thy comelineſs is nothing leſſe</l>
                  <l>Then is the fair <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt in right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and daily obſerving the ſame, thereby is and becomes a terrour to all that hate her on every ſide.</note>Thou terrifi'ſt thine enemies</l>
                  <l>And makeſt them full ſore afraid</l>
                  <l>As armed men: do others when</l>
                  <l>Their banners be in feild diſplay'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Jeſus Chriſt doth yield up himſelf as one captivated by, and to the faith of every true believer.</note>Now turn aſide: my lovely bride</l>
                  <l>For with thy eyes I'm vanquiſht quite</l>
                  <l>And conquer'd I: do wounded lye</l>
                  <l>With that which is my hearts delight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">See, chapter 4th ver. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>Thy well-ſet hair: that mad'ſt thee fair</l>
                  <l>Moſt fitly I may it compare</l>
                  <l>Unto the flocks: that on the rocks</l>
                  <l>And mounts of <hi>Gilead,</hi> grazing are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">See chap. <hi>4.</hi> ver. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note>Thy teeth appear, like ſheep when th'are</l>
                  <l>New waſht and clipt and even ſhorn</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt whom there is no barrenneſſe</l>
                  <l>For each one of them twins have born.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104634:15"/>
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">See chap. <hi>4.</hi> ver. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>Thy temples bright: (are like inſight)</l>
                  <l>To a pomgranate cut in peices</l>
                  <l>And thou doſt cover them all over</l>
                  <l>Within thy locks and hairy fleeces.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>The queens that be: ate full ſixty</l>
                  <l>And fourſcore Concubins in count</l>
                  <l>The virgins fine: that with them joyn</l>
                  <l>All numbers farr they do furmount.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Believers though of never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſwaſions, yet are all one in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhould labour after oneneſs amongſt themſelves, and preſerve the unity of the ſpirtt in the bond of peace.</note>But my dear love and ſpotles dove</l>
                  <l>She is but one the choyce alone</l>
                  <l>Of her dear mother and there's no other</l>
                  <l>That did for her in travail groan.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">The ſpiritual glory of Chriſts Church beſpeaks her bleſſedneſs, is worthy of admiration and praiſe from all others.</note>When they beheld her that exceld</l>
                  <l>Both daughters queens and concubines</l>
                  <l>Themſelves did raiſe to bleſs and praiſe</l>
                  <l>Her, that ſo much in glory ſhines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt in all ſtates hath a ſpiritual brightneſs, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more dim, ſomtimes more clear, and ſhines more and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perfect day.</note>Oh who is ſhee that we do ſee</l>
                  <l>Like to the morning looking bright</l>
                  <l>Fair as the moon which light full ſoon</l>
                  <l>Expels the darkneſs of the night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſun ſo clear doth not appear</l>
                  <l>More glorious and beſide what's ſaid</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">See ver. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note>She terifies her enemies</l>
                  <l>As armies do with flags diſplayd</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is his garden in which he is converſant, delighted much with the good fruit brought forth thereby, hath a ſpecial eye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her, looking for her fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, growth and increaſe.</note>I went to ſee the fruits that be</l>
                  <l>I'th vallies and the gardens too</l>
                  <l>The fruitful vine to flouriſh fine</l>
                  <l>And the pomegranates bud and blow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>Such was my care that ere aware</l>
                  <l>Like th'chariots of <hi>Aminadad</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My ſoul did drive me for to ſtrive</l>
                  <l>T'expreſs the love I ever had.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">The beſt for want of care and watchfulneſs may ſlip and fall, but it is both their duty and property to return from evil when rowzed up and cal'd upon.</note>If thou haſt been inclin'd to ſin</l>
                  <l>Return, return oh <hi>Shulamite</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tis bad to ſtray worſe there to ſtay</l>
                  <l>Return we dearly thee invite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104634:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently every Chriſtian is both love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and humble, hath enemies fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without, and two contrary parties oppoſing each other within.</note>What would ye ſee in me to be</l>
                  <l>Poor love debaſed <hi>Shulamite</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But companies of two armies</l>
                  <l>Who with each other dayly fight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>OH princes daughter great</l>
                  <l>Heir to the king of kings</l>
                  <l>Thou gloriouſly compleat</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">It is no ſmall part of a Chriſtians glory, to continue patiently in well doing, and for the ſame bear to and undergo all things impoſ'd upon them.</note>Appeareſt in all things.</l>
                  <l>Thy feet are ſhod</l>
                  <l>With Goſpel peace that thou with eaſe</l>
                  <l>Maiſt walk with God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt a ſpiritual body, faſhion'd form'd knit &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted together by the worker of all things, acting in all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his apoyntments.</note>The joynts within thy thighs</l>
                  <l>Like jewels are and chains</l>
                  <l>All wrought in curious-wife</l>
                  <l>By th'cunning workmans pains</l>
                  <l>Each ſeveral joynt</l>
                  <l>Of my body doth ſupply</l>
                  <l>As I appoint.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Bleſſed is he that believeth and is baptized: for he is waſhed from his ſins and ſhall have life everlaſting.</note>Thy navel firm and ſound</l>
                  <l>That liquor wanteth none</l>
                  <l>Is like a goblet round</l>
                  <l>Refreſhing every one</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hearts I raiſe</l>
                  <l>To paſs the flood that ſhews my blood</l>
                  <l>For ſins releaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">The ordinances of Chriſt in his Church do nouriſh refreſh ſuccour ſupport, comfort and edify the ſaints, when ſpiritually, carefully, conſcientiouſly they feed upon them.</note>Thy belly like to wheat</l>
                  <l>With lillys white ſet ore</l>
                  <l>Affords moſt precious meat</l>
                  <l>In great abundant ſtore</l>
                  <l>To be kept ſtill</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104634:16"/>
                  <l>That all my Saints that be in wants</l>
                  <l>May feed their fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">See chap. the <hi>4</hi> and ver. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note>Thy breſts are like two twins</l>
                  <l>Of yong and tender roes</l>
                  <l>From whence becauſe of ſins</l>
                  <l>Rivers of comforts flows</l>
                  <l>To ſouls oppreſt</l>
                  <l>For ther's no other but thou their mother</l>
                  <l>Can give them reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Thoſe whoſe ſouls are freed from ſpiritual ſlavery and bondage by Chriſt Ieſus, become powerful, and able to do or undergo whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he calls them unto.</note>Thy neck that ſhews thy power</l>
                  <l>Being freed from ſlavery</l>
                  <l>Is like an ivory tower</l>
                  <l>Rais'd up moſt ſtrong and high</l>
                  <l>(Sins cruel bands</l>
                  <l>Are like a yoke but they are broke</l>
                  <l>By Gods commands.)</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">See chap. <hi>4</hi> and ver. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>Thy eyes that give thee light</l>
                  <l>Tranſparent are and clear</l>
                  <l>Like to the fiſhponds bright</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Heſhbon</hi> that appear</l>
                  <l>Cloſe by the gate</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Bethrabbin</hi> where men go in</l>
                  <l>And out thereat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpirit vigilant and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, wiſely foreſees the evil and in a prudent way delivers her ſelf from it.</note>Thy noſe is like the tower</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Lebanon</hi> ſo high</l>
                  <l>From whence the foes great power</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Siria</hi> men did ſpy</l>
                  <l>Thou cry'ſt arm arm</l>
                  <l>Leſt enemies when they do riſe</l>
                  <l>Should do thee harm.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Chriſt is the head of his Church he both rules and governs her, is alſo her defence and glory.</note>Thy head that ruleth well.</l>
                  <l>The reſt of thy body</l>
                  <l>Is like unto <hi>Carmel</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In glorious dignity</l>
                  <l>Thy hair alſo</l>
                  <l>Upon thy head: like purple red</l>
                  <l>Doth neatly grow.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104634:16"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">The ſpiritual glory which Chriſt hath put upon his Church, is a thing that holds him in continual delight, and greateſt pleaſure.</note>The beauty which thou haſt</l>
                  <l>It doth me captivate</l>
                  <l>That I am held full faſt</l>
                  <l>In a delightful ſtate</l>
                  <l>Of ſweeteſt pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Each ſight of thee affecteth me</l>
                  <l>Above all meaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Chriſt ſtill affected with the Churches beauty continues or rather renews his praiſes of her.</note>How fair art thou my dear</l>
                  <l>For pleaſure of each kinde</l>
                  <l>Such beauty any where</l>
                  <l>I yet could never finde</l>
                  <l>I muſt admire</l>
                  <l>Thy comelines: which I profeſs</l>
                  <l>My heart doth fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt holds faſt what ſhe has received; will grow in grace and ſpiritually flouriſh, though adverſarys riſe up againſt her to depreſſe, keep down or root her up.</note>Thy ſtature's like the tree</l>
                  <l>Whereon the palms do grow</l>
                  <l>That flouriſhing will be</l>
                  <l>Though men will keep it low</l>
                  <l>Like grapes well fild</l>
                  <l>Thy breſts are ſuch: and comfort much</l>
                  <l>To ſouls they yeild.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Chriſt being aſcended on high will have a ſpecial eye to his Church; preſerve her from evil, comfort in and under her trouble and make her abundantly fruitful in good.</note>To th' palm-tree I will go</l>
                  <l>For it is my decree</l>
                  <l>To comfort mine, and to</l>
                  <l>Protect and overſee</l>
                  <l>Each bough ſo green</l>
                  <l>I'le take and dreſs: that fruitfulneſſe</l>
                  <l>May there be ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Thoſe cannot be barren but aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in all good fruit over whom Chriſt hath a ſpiritual eye with whom he is in ſweet Communion.</note>Like cluſters of the vine</l>
                  <l>Now ſhall thy breſts be ſuch</l>
                  <l>There is not one of mine</l>
                  <l>But fruit is yeelding much</l>
                  <l>They do abound;</l>
                  <l>In heavenly grace: that have my face</l>
                  <l>And favour found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104634:17"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Thoſe that are faithful labourers in the Lords work ſhall not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out honour here and a great reward hereafter.</note>Thy noſe like apples ſweet</l>
                  <l>Doth ſend it's ſmell abroad</l>
                  <l>Great fame is for them meet</l>
                  <l>That watch the flock of God</l>
                  <l>Their memory</l>
                  <l>It ſhall be bleſt: when they in reſt</l>
                  <l>And ſilence lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Saints of all ſorts have learn'd the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> their mouths fild with words full of goodneſſe, ſpeeches gracious, tending to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy all that hear them.</note>The pallate of thy mouth</l>
                  <l>Is like the pureſt wine</l>
                  <l>Thy words are for thy growth</l>
                  <l>And edifying mine</l>
                  <l>It glads their heart</l>
                  <l>And doth enlive; like wine revive</l>
                  <l>Them in each part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">The word of the Lord is quick and powerful; of a piercing divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſcerning nature ſo known to thoſe that feel the vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note>How efficacious then</l>
                  <l>Are words thou giveſt forth</l>
                  <l>They pleaſe me and all men</l>
                  <l>That taſt their precious worth</l>
                  <l>Their power is much</l>
                  <l>If men digeſt: what's ſoundly preſt</l>
                  <l>Their ſouls to touch.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Thoſe that have taſted of the good word of the Lord and felt the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power thereof will not cannot be be ſilent but declare to others; what God hath done for their ſouls.</note>For it the ſleep doth break</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe that ſleepy are</l>
                  <l>Cauſing their lips to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>In praiſes and in prayer</l>
                  <l>They'l publiſh ſoon</l>
                  <l>And tell abroad: the things that God</l>
                  <l>For them hath done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">When ſouls partake of the ſweetneſs of Chriſts love, they are then caryed forth to give up themſelves to him, becoming wholy his.</note>Now my aſſurance is</l>
                  <l>(From it i'le not be mov'd)</l>
                  <l>That <hi>I</hi> am wholy his</l>
                  <l>That is my beſt belov'd</l>
                  <l>And yet more ſee</l>
                  <l>His whole deſire: which <hi>I</hi> admire</l>
                  <l>Is toward me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104634:17"/>
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Chriſt is a Chriſtians beſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion whoſe preſence they beg and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ize above all things elſe.</note>Now come with me my dear</l>
                  <l>Let's go into the field,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">Goſpel fruit is moſt pleaſing to, and acceptable to Chriſt Jeſus.</note>The fruit, that's gathe'rd there</l>
                  <l>Doth great contentment yeild</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">The poor low and humble in ſpirit, and places mean and poor are fit receptacles for Jeſus Chriſt.</note>Let's lodge and reſt</l>
                  <l>In places poor: for they full ſure</l>
                  <l>By thee are bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Thoſe ſouls that have miſcarryed, and are once humbled for it, will be diligent for time to come.</note>Oh let us riſe betime</l>
                  <l>And to the vinyards go</l>
                  <l>Much ſleeping was the crime</l>
                  <l>That made my heart full wo</l>
                  <l>Let's up and ſee.</l>
                  <l>(Though ſome repines) whether the vines</l>
                  <l>Flouriſhing be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">The ſtronger the Chriſtians are and moſt indued with grace, the greater care will they have of thoſe that are weak and tender in the growth of Chriſtianity.</note>Whether the grape ſo young</l>
                  <l>And tender be in growth</l>
                  <l>And pomgranate among</l>
                  <l>The other fruits bud forth</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">All that the ſaints have or can do is too little for Chriſt; hence it is they reſigne all they have unto him; who is worthy of more then they have or can give.</note>There <hi>I</hi> am free</l>
                  <l>For to reſigne: all that is mine</l>
                  <l>My loves to thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">The ſaints are always ready and prepared; with oyl in their lamps furniſht with all things excellent, to meet and entertain Chriſt Jeſus.</note>The mandraks ſweetly ſmell</l>
                  <l>And at our gates be there</l>
                  <l>Such things as moſt execl</l>
                  <l>And for thee ready are</l>
                  <l>Fruits of all kinde</l>
                  <l>That can be told: both new and old</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt there finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Saints do all they do for and unto Chriſt, have received of his full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and return to him, and lay up for him as it is their duty, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thankfulneſſe and love.</note>Which <hi>I</hi> lay up and ſave</l>
                  <l>As in a treaſure</l>
                  <l>The choyceſt that <hi>I</hi> have</l>
                  <l>Is not too good for thee</l>
                  <l>None can me move</l>
                  <l>But had <hi>I</hi> more: I would it ſtore</l>
                  <l>For my dear love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104634:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt is ever deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Communion with him, do rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily embrace him, cheerfully obey him, not mattering the worlds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches.</note>OH that thou werſt, even as my brother dear</l>
                  <l>That ſuckt the breſts, of her that did me bear</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>I</hi> ſhould find thee, there <hi>I</hi> would thee kiſs</l>
                  <l>And ſhould not be deſpis'd a jot for this.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Chriſtians having found and layd hold on Chriſt, hold him faſt, will not let him go: ſtill deſirous of his preſence.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> would thee lead, and bring thee to no other</l>
                  <l>But to the manſions of my own ſweet mother</l>
                  <l>Thither full readily, I will conduct thee</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">The truths of Chriſt for inſtruction correction and comfort are.</note>And there full readily, ſhe will inſtruct me,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Kept and to be found in his Church every true Chriſtian hath the pure juyces of faith obedience and love to pleaſe and delight Chriſt.</note>There of pure ſpiced wine; I'le make thee drink</l>
                  <l>And of pomgranate juyce, for why <hi>I</hi> think</l>
                  <l>Thou well deſerv'ſt to drink the ſweet'ſt of all</l>
                  <l>Though ſome once gave thee vinegar and gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Saints as they want and ſtand in need of Chriſts power to ſupport and ſtrengthen them: they may be aſſured to have and injoy in all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note>Now that <hi>I</hi> may not want my full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</l>
                  <l>His left hand ſhall my feeble head ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</l>
                  <l>To chear my heart, his right hand ſhall embrace me</l>
                  <l>That neither ſin nor weakneſs do diſgrace me</l>
                  <l>Such cloſe embraces: <hi>I</hi> can tell by trying</l>
                  <l>They will revive a fainting ſoul a dying.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104634:18"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">See chap. <hi>2</hi> and <hi>7</hi> ver.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> charge, adjure, and do forbid all them</l>
                  <l>That are cal'd daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They ſtir not up my love, by wicked ways</l>
                  <l>Nor him awake until himſelf do pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>For whoſoever doth him ſo provoke</l>
                  <l>Muſt feel the force of his moſt angry ſtroak.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">See chap. <hi>3</hi> and <hi>6</hi> ver.</note>Oh who is this, we cannot but admire</l>
                  <l>That doth aſcend; and riſe up daily higher</l>
                  <l>Out of the deſart forlorn wilderneſs,</l>
                  <l>Into a ſtate of happineſs and bliſs;</l>
                  <l>For ſhe both lies and leans, and ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends</l>
                  <l>Upon her beſt belov'd as ſhe aſcends.</l>
                  <l>She reſts, ſhe rowls ſhe hopes, on him ſhe ſtays</l>
                  <l>That her upholds, and keeps in all her ways</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">By Jeſus Chriſt all his are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally raiſed from a dead and filthy ſtate to live a new life here and ſhall by him be rais'd again at the laſt day.</note>When thou waſt fal'n my ſpouſe; I pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed thee</l>
                  <l>And rais'd thee from under the apple tree</l>
                  <l>There did thy mother, bear and bring thee forth,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch uncleanneſſe as my ſoul did loath;</l>
                  <l>But through my blood and paſſion, thou and ſhe</l>
                  <l>From ſin and death, are perfectly ſet free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Chriſts favours conferd upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are ſtrong obligations to love and thinkfulneſs.</note>Now ſith thou haſt, for me ſo great things done</l>
                  <l>My heart thou haſt, for everlaſting won;</l>
                  <l>And now I beg and pray, dear love to be</l>
                  <l>Yet more aſſur'd; how well thou loveſt me</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">To be in, and upon the heart of Chriſt is the great priviledge, and earneſt deſire of every Chriſtian.</note>And therefore ſet me as a ſeal is ſet,</l>
                  <l>Upon thy heart that thou maiſt not forget</l>
                  <l>Thy kindneſs to me and t'free me from harm</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104634:19"/>
                  <l>Set me alſo, as ſeal upon thine arme.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">That true divine ſpiritual love which is ſhed abroad in the hearts of the ſaints, is powerful, conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and of a durable laſting na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note>For why, the love I bear to thee my dear</l>
                  <l>It is for ſtrength much like the king of fear</l>
                  <l>Whoſe deadly fatall ſtroak kills all; but I</l>
                  <l>If thou deny my ſuit for love muſt dye;</l>
                  <l>For like the grave that cruelly devours</l>
                  <l>And every living creature overpowers,</l>
                  <l>Such is the zeal and love within my breſt</l>
                  <l>It quite conſumes me, I can have no reſt</l>
                  <l>The coals thereof; are coals of heavenly fire</l>
                  <l>Whoſe burning flames do mount my ſoul up higher</l>
                  <l>This works, this ſhines, this upward flys</l>
                  <l>This burning lyes, and lives when t'other dyes</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">There is no calamity miſery or affliction, no perſecution ſo great that can extinguiſh the fire of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine loue to Chriſt Jeſus.</note>Though men and devils daily go about</l>
                  <l>Thinking to quench, extinguiſh and put out</l>
                  <l>This heavenly flame of love by often trying</l>
                  <l>By feirce affliction whether 'twill be dying</l>
                  <l>Though many floods and waters overflow it;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">The more the Church of Chriſt is perſecuted the more it flouriſhes.</note>The more they ſeek to quench the more they blow it</l>
                  <l>Into a perfect flame of love divine</l>
                  <l>To him, that loves not leſs, for ought that's mine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Where there is true love to Jeſus Chriſt, it will make them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, deſpiſe, yea to hate all things in compariſon of him.</note>Such is the ſtrength of love, and more behold</l>
                  <l>Not pearls nor precious ſtones nor pureſt gold</l>
                  <l>Can force or flatter me to be diſloyall</l>
                  <l>My love is ſtronger and can bide the tryal</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104634:19"/>
                  <l>It hates, it ſcorns, it loaths that mans great riches</l>
                  <l>Or ſubſtance of his houſe which ſome bewitches</l>
                  <l>To turn aſide: yet though 'twere offer'd to me</l>
                  <l>I would condemn and put it away from me</l>
                  <l>So high is my reſolve I do diſdain</l>
                  <l>All things for Chriſt for whom all loſs is gain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">True love to Chriſt, draws out the heart to love others alſo, to pitty them, pray for them; and ſeek by all means their everlaſting well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</note>Thus unto thee my love I have expreſt</l>
                  <l>And yet with thee alone; it muſt not reſt</l>
                  <l>I am conſtrain'd by it to make petition</l>
                  <l>For our poor ſiſter whoſe yet low condition</l>
                  <l>Requires thy pitty for ſhe is but ſmall</l>
                  <l>And little too: having no breſts at all</l>
                  <l>To yeild refreſhment: oh what ſhall we do</l>
                  <l>What grace deſire; what furtherance yeild unto</l>
                  <l>Our little ſiſter for whom 'tis our care</l>
                  <l>That ſhe, and we at laſt, alike may fare;</l>
                  <l>Oh think upon her; do her not forget</l>
                  <l>She now is low but thou her time haſt ſet</l>
                  <l>When thou wilt for her ſpeak, and ſomthing ſay</l>
                  <l>To ſhew thy grace, in her appointed day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt hath a wall for defence, a door for entrance, admiſſion and excluſion, is diſtinct from others by obedience to Chriſts laws and holyneſs: ſurrounded on every ſide with the never fading mercys and favours of God.</note>If that ſhe be a wall for ſo we would</l>
                  <l>Have her to be: then upon her we could</l>
                  <l>As on a firm foundation raiſe and build</l>
                  <l>Such palaces, as ſilver pure doth yeild</l>
                  <l>Let's her divide, from others by a name</l>
                  <l>And then increaſe her glory to her fame:</l>
                  <l>And if ſhe be, or have a door which ſhows</l>
                  <l>The building perfected as each man knows</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104634:20"/>
                  <l>Oh when we can but ſee her this compleat</l>
                  <l>Then will we compaſs her, with mercys great</l>
                  <l>Which will endure, and are more laſting farr</l>
                  <l>Then all, or any boards of cedar are</l>
                  <l>No gates, or ſtrength of hell ſhall once prevail</l>
                  <l>To do her any harm: though they aſſayl</l>
                  <l>Her with great force: for ſhe's the habitation</l>
                  <l>Of him that makes her gates; and wals Salvation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Chriſtians are then both amiable and uſeful when grown well in grace being united by faith and obedience are ſtedfaſt and immoveable.</note>Now I am grown; into a perfect wall</l>
                  <l>(Such growth all have, that hearken to Chriſts call)</l>
                  <l>My breſts like towers, they are erected high</l>
                  <l>Others to help, my ſelf to beautify</l>
                  <l>Now I am knit unto the corner ſtone</l>
                  <l>My ground-work's ſure, and cannot be o'rethrown.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Men in a natural ſtate are filthy impure unpoliſht rough, unlovely but partaking of the grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus unto converſion and faith are moſt precious and ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him.</note>From that time I found favor in his eyes</l>
                  <l>(Though once I was, like ſtones that men deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>When they among the rubbiſh lye unſquar'd</l>
                  <l>Such was my ſtate, and ſo it with me far'd</l>
                  <l>But now being hewn, and ſquar'd, and poliſht bright)</l>
                  <l>I am become ſo precious in his ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Thoſe Chriſt imploys in his vineyard ought to be both vigilant, laborious diligent.</note>At <hi>Baalhamon,</hi> a fertile fruitful plot</l>
                  <l>A fruitful vineyard <hi>Solomon</hi> had got</l>
                  <l>Which vineyard he lets out unto his keepers</l>
                  <l>Which muſt be watchmen, and not drowſy ſleepers</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104634:20"/>
                  <l>And every one of them muſt yearly bring</l>
                  <l>Forth fruit thereof, a thouſand ſilverling.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">The Church of Chriſt, and ſo every Chriſtian is Chriſts own and ought to be devoted wholy unto him.</note>The vineyard t'wich I have a proper right</l>
                  <l>It is my own and always in my ſight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">He hath promiſt his preſence with his people and will make proviſion for them.</note>My watchful eye her wants ſhall ſtill be ſpying</l>
                  <l>And when diſcern'd my grace ſhall be ſupplying</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wants of hers: that ſhe may fruitful be</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">To the end they may abound in Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel fruit in good works.</note>And in great meaſure bring forth fruit to me</l>
                  <l>Her bleſſing is proſperity and peace</l>
                  <l>And I expect and look for much increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Not for my ſelf alone nor for my ſake</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">The labourers in Chriſts Church are bleſſed if faithful, for they ſhall have a great reward.</note>But fellow laborers, that pain do take</l>
                  <l>To dig, and plant and prune without regard</l>
                  <l>Unto themſelves: ſure I will them reward</l>
                  <l>If I a thouſand do look for at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Two hundred to allow them <hi>I</hi> am pleaſt</l>
                  <l>They ſhall partake o'th glory that is mine</l>
                  <l>And like the ſun in brightneſs ever ſhine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">The true Church of Chriſt and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> paſtours thereof teach and inſtruct others with ſaving doctrine and ſound ſpeech ſuch as cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned.</note>O thou that in the gardens, haſt thy dwelling</l>
                  <l>Regard this thing, which to thee I am telling</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt companions, which do heare thy voyce</l>
                  <l>And thou muſt them inſtruct, for therein lyes</l>
                  <l>Thy duty to them: thou muſt ſet before them</l>
                  <l>The good and evil too, not Lord ore them</l>
                  <l>For they partake of the ſame precious faith</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104634:21"/>
                  <l>And what the one have, ſtill the other hath</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">To be much in prayer is the duty of Saints, it is the precept of Chriſt, and pleaſing to him if they do ſo.</note>And furthermore, thou mayſt cauſe me to hear</l>
                  <l>Thy voyce alſo, in humble hearty prayer</l>
                  <l>It is a ſacrifice, right pleaſant ſweet</l>
                  <l>And for the ſaints to offer it is meet</l>
                  <l>My ſoul alſo with it is much delighted</l>
                  <l>Remember how to it thou art invited.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Every gracious ſoul longs and prays for Chriſts ſecond coming in glory, that they may be freed from all that is greivous here &amp; reign with him in heaven hereafter: amen, come Lord Jeſus come quickly.</note>My ſoul dear love's impatient of delay</l>
                  <l>Make haſt, make haſt, and do no longer ſtay</l>
                  <l>Be thou for ſwiftneſs like the roe or hart</l>
                  <l>My only dear who on the mountains art</l>
                  <l>Of ſpicy pleaſures and all rare delight</l>
                  <l>That raviſh will the heart: and dim the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of all beholders from thoſe glorious hills</l>
                  <l>The ſweteſt pleaſures evermore diſtills;</l>
                  <l>While I am here below I am oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Lord Jeſus quickly come, to give me reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Jonah" type="biblical_paraphrase">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104634:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE BOOK OF JONAH IN MEETRE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>How <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſent to <hi>Niniveh</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But he withſtood Gods call,</l>
                  <l>In turning off another way,</l>
                  <l>And's ſwallowed by a whale.</l>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN antient times as Scriptures do record</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Iſra'l</hi> dwelt a prophet of the Lord.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jona</hi> by name, ſon of Amittais youth,</l>
                  <l>To whom the Lord ſent forth his word of truth,</l>
                  <l>He long had preacht to <hi>Iſra'ls</hi> ten tribes</l>
                  <l>Converts them not, but gains their mocks and gibes;</l>
                  <l>Now God doth ſee by means they do not profit</l>
                  <l>When they ſhould hear the word, they rather ſcof it,</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:104634:22"/>
                  <l>Their hearts are hard, means makes them not amend</l>
                  <l>Another way God will their prophet ſend:</l>
                  <l>The light from heaven muſt not always ſhine</l>
                  <l>What God doth give he ſometimes takes again.<note place="margin">Obſervation from Gods ſending <hi>Jonah</hi> to <hi>Niniveh</hi> out of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he preacht but did not profit.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When trees are barren, do not bring forth fruit</l>
                  <l>The gardener will pluck 'em up by the root,</l>
                  <l>When men have means for growth, but do not grow</l>
                  <l>God will not ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y but away will go,</l>
                  <l>When truth appears but truth men do not love</l>
                  <l>Nor means nor mercies, carefully improve</l>
                  <l>For their cheif good: their day is turn'd to night</l>
                  <l>And darkneſs covers them inſtead of light;</l>
                  <l>The means they had before God will remove it,</l>
                  <l>And give it thoſe that better will improve it;</l>
                  <l>When by the means they do not bring forth fruit</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſhall have means, that by the means will do't</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On mine embaſſage <hi>Jona</hi> thou muſt go</l>
                  <l>And haſt away th' aſſirian city to</l>
                  <l>That is ſo great, ſo full, and of ſuch fame</l>
                  <l>Through all the world: 'tis <hi>Niniveh</hi> by name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when thou comeſt there in herald-wiſe</l>
                  <l>Declare thy meſſage, though they do deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>Both it and thee: lift up thy voice on high</l>
                  <l>And like a trumpet, ſound a fearfull cry</l>
                  <l>Againſt the city, leſt it doth repent</l>
                  <l>And let it know, for what end thou art ſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For why, I judge them not without a cauſe</l>
                  <l>The people are found bteakers of my laws,</l>
                  <l>They have not lern'd to fear nor to adore me</l>
                  <l>Their wickedneſs and ſin, it lies before me,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſins once cry'd lowd in mine ears</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Ninivehs</hi> before my face appears,</l>
                  <l>For which I will the city overthrow</l>
                  <l>Commiſſion now thou haſt, ſee that thou go;</l>
                  <l>The greateſt monarchs that the earth doth bear</l>
                  <l>Nor Citys of moſt fame that ever were</l>
                  <l>Nor might nor greatneſs gives immunity</l>
                  <l>But all expos'd to judgment juſt they ly;<note place="margin">Obſervation from Gods not ſparing the greateſt places nor perſons.</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104634:22"/>
                  <l>If they minde not their maker for to know</l>
                  <l>Their makers minde is them to overthrow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Jona</hi> now as one amaz'd no doubt,</l>
                  <l>With this ſtrange heathen news doth caſt about</l>
                  <l>What courſe to take, that ſo he may not be</l>
                  <l>A bringer of this news to <hi>Ninivee;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For why, in <hi>Iſrael</hi> he had taken pain</l>
                  <l>And preached long; but's preaching was in vain</l>
                  <l>Doth thoſe elaborate pains, convert no Jews</l>
                  <l>What hope is there that this unwelcome news,</l>
                  <l>This dreadful, direful ſermon ſhould finde place</l>
                  <l>Among the people of the heathen race</l>
                  <l>And if it ſhould then God was gracious bent</l>
                  <l>And of the threatned judgment would repent</l>
                  <l>That ſo his reputation he muſt loſe</l>
                  <l>Another way therefore the prophet goes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When doubts ariſe and dangers ſtand before</l>
                  <l>Seeming to croſs the way we ſhould go ore</l>
                  <l>When at the ſtake our carnal intereſt lies</l>
                  <l>And ſelf muſt ſuffer by the enterprize</l>
                  <l>How apt are we poor weaklings to ſuggeſt</l>
                  <l>Our own devices, not Gods ways the beſt.<note place="margin">Obſervation from <hi>Jonah's</hi> turning aſide becauſe he thought God would not make good his word againſt <hi>Niniveh.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sin blinds mens eyes, now <hi>Iona</hi> thinks to flee</l>
                  <l>Out of his preſence who doth view and ſee</l>
                  <l>Each ſtep he takes: from his all-ſeeing eyes</l>
                  <l>He poſts away; and unto <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> flyes</l>
                  <l>Having caſt off obedience to Gods word</l>
                  <l>He ſteals away from ſerving of his Lord</l>
                  <l>Thinking that by this unadviſed flight</l>
                  <l>To hide himſelf from Gods moſt peircing ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To a ſea port or to a haven town</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iopa</hi> by name, this paſſenger went down,</l>
                  <l>At his arival there he quickly ſound</l>
                  <l>A ſhip prepared; fitted, ready bound</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Tarſus</hi> citty: there her voyage was</l>
                  <l>Thither the rebell Prophet thought to paſs;</l>
                  <l>And that his paſſage might not be prevented</l>
                  <l>To pay his fare, aforehand hee's contented</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104634:23"/>
                  <l>Which having done he quickly goes aboard</l>
                  <l>To flee away from ſerving of the Lord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When ſelf ſits uppermoſt and beareth ſway</l>
                  <l>That ſelfiſh ſoul will quickly diſobey</l>
                  <l>Gods juſt commands:<note place="margin">Obſervation from <hi>Jonah's</hi> care and diligence to effect his carnal intention.</note> and every holy teſt</l>
                  <l>For to promote a ſelfiſh intereſt.</l>
                  <l>No let nor rub that ſtandeth in the way</l>
                  <l>Of erring man; when once he goes aſtray</l>
                  <l>From Gods command: but he with diligence</l>
                  <l>Will uſe endeavour, to remove it thence</l>
                  <l>What care he takes for fear his game be loſt,</l>
                  <l>Although at laſt full dear it do him coſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jona</hi> haſts away, hee's under ſayl</l>
                  <l>Looking each minute for a proſperous gale</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſant winde to further his intent,</l>
                  <l>And quickly waf't him ore whether he went.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But that great Lord whom <hi>Jona</hi> did diſpleaſe</l>
                  <l>Sent out his winde and did a tempeſt raiſe,</l>
                  <l>A mighty tempeſt is upon the main</l>
                  <l>So that the ſhip the clouds do ſeem to gain:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe milder ſtreams are curl'd, rough and unkinde</l>
                  <l>And rage and ſwell by reaſon of the winde</l>
                  <l>The Ship it reels like to a drunken man,</l>
                  <l>The mariners they do all that they can</l>
                  <l>To lowr the top-ſail, and take in the ſails</l>
                  <l>Yet all they do or can nothing avails</l>
                  <l>For ſtill the hideous tempeſt on them lyes</l>
                  <l>And to loſe ſhip and all, now each man crys.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How vain are we to think our counſel will</l>
                  <l>Take place:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods croſſing <hi>Jonah</hi> in his way of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and rebellion.</note> when we conſult for to fulfil</l>
                  <l>Unruly luſts, and fooliſh fond intent,</l>
                  <l>Thinking Gods bleſſed will for to prevent</l>
                  <l>Then to our grief, our detriment and loſs,</l>
                  <l>Such purpoſes, he'l quickly croſs;</l>
                  <l>All mens endeavours then are at a ſtand</l>
                  <l>When they endeavour to bind up God hand</l>
                  <l>Or to divert the courſe of a juſt rod,</l>
                  <l>When ſtreached forth by a diſpleaſed God</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104634:23"/>
                  <l>The ſeamen all are now full ſore afraid</l>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt hearts of men may be diſmayd</l>
                  <l>Fear with the ſmart of heavens chaſtizing rod</l>
                  <l>Drives every man to call upon his God:</l>
                  <l>Unto their heathen gods they make their ſuit,</l>
                  <l>Fear makes men pray, when nothing elſe will do't,</l>
                  <l>And now as men poſſeſt with dreadful cares</l>
                  <l>To ſave themſelves and ſhip: they take the wares</l>
                  <l>And caſt it over board; in hope their pains</l>
                  <l>May be rewarded in the uſe of means.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some that confeſſe a God:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the heathen Seamens praying in danger</note> no more God knows</l>
                  <l>Then did theſe heathen rude and barbarous,</l>
                  <l>Who in the time of their great miſery</l>
                  <l>Do all confeſſe there is a deity.</l>
                  <l>But they that do confeſſe the true God muſt</l>
                  <l>Fear, love, obey, and always in him truſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But where is <hi>Jona</hi> all this dreadful while</l>
                  <l>The Seas do roar and rage and foam and boyl,</l>
                  <l>And whiſtling winds a fearful noyſe do keep</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Ionas</hi> gone aſide the ſhip to ſleep,</l>
                  <l>His ſences are lockt faſt, and conſcience too</l>
                  <l>And neither wakes for all the ſeas can do.</l>
                  <l>A man would think no heart could now endure</l>
                  <l>But ſin makes men moſt deſperatly ſecure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When into dangers men are plunged deep</l>
                  <l>They many times do fall full faſt aſleep</l>
                  <l>Lul'd in the cradle of ſecurity</l>
                  <l>Till their ſmall threed of life be cut,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in time of ſo great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> whereby</l>
                  <l>They hold their leaſe, then they awakned be:</l>
                  <l>Eyes that were ſhut, are open now to ſee</l>
                  <l>How Sathan like a jugler, did deceive them</l>
                  <l>And of true happineſſe did quite bereave them,</l>
                  <l>Who being fool'd into this diſmal ſtate</l>
                  <l>Muſt pay for pleaſures at a woful rate,</l>
                  <l>The maſter of the Ship then to him came</l>
                  <l>And ſays what meaneſt thou (O fy for ſhame)</l>
                  <l>What meaneſt thou O ſleeper void of fears)</l>
                  <l>How canſt thou, darſt thou reſt, now death appears?</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104634:24"/>
                  <l>Are not we ſinking all into the deep</l>
                  <l>Why doſt not rather watch: but ly and ſleep?</l>
                  <l>Is this a time for thee to be ſecure</l>
                  <l>Now death is wayting for thee at the door?</l>
                  <l>Art thou of ſence and reaſon quite bereft</l>
                  <l>Or of the world to come, all thoughts haſt left?</l>
                  <l>Ariſe O ſluggard, do it not delay</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou a God, then unto thy God pray</l>
                  <l>And call upon him with an earneſt cry</l>
                  <l>Perhaps he'l hear and will us not deſtroy:</l>
                  <l>Thus did the heathen to his duty move him</l>
                  <l>And for his negligence ſharply reprove him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come near and take a veiw;<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the prophets ſluggiſhneſſe who was to have been a watchman unto others.</note> but do not wonder</l>
                  <l>To ſee a Boanarges ſon of thunder;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe office is to cry to men, arm, arm,</l>
                  <l>Leſt through ſecurity your ſouls take harm:</l>
                  <l>Stand faſt, quit you like men, be ſtrong and watch:</l>
                  <l>And yet himſelf a ſingle ſlumber catch</l>
                  <l>His light, his life, his grace a while to ſmother</l>
                  <l>In aſhes rak't, till kindled by another.</l>
                  <l>O moſt prodigious, he that is the keeper</l>
                  <l>Of's own and others ſouls to turn dead ſleeper.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſeamen now agaſt, with horrid fear</l>
                  <l>Did think ſome wicked perſon was come there</l>
                  <l>Who had committed ſome more huinous crime</l>
                  <l>And for whoſe cauſe the evil of that time</l>
                  <l>Had now befaln them: hence with one conſent</l>
                  <l>They all agree to finde the delinquent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come let us now caſt lots into the lap</l>
                  <l>Thereby to know for whoſe cauſe this miſhap</l>
                  <l>And evil is upon us: ſo they fell</l>
                  <l>To caſting lots: till that time none could tell</l>
                  <l>Who was the man ſo ſorely had offended,</l>
                  <l>The lot was caſt, and <hi>Iona</hi> apprehended;</l>
                  <l>When God will execute his judgments juſt</l>
                  <l>'Tis a vain thing in a vain thing to truſt;<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> being found out by the Lord and his ſin diſcovered.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When God a ſinner will bring to the tryal</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thing to bid the Lord denial</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104634:24"/>
                  <l>When God will ſerch 'tis vain to go about</l>
                  <l>To hide from God; for God will finde it out.</l>
                  <l>Shall vain man ſin? in ſinning think to hide</l>
                  <l>Himſelf from God; whoſe eyes cannot abide</l>
                  <l>To look on ſin, what doth he think he can</l>
                  <l>Deal with his God, as he dealeth with man?</l>
                  <l>Nay God hath ways and means to bring to light,</l>
                  <l>Things done in ſecret and the darkſome night,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes by this means, and ſometimes by th'other</l>
                  <l>God will diſcover what vain man doth ſmother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now let us know, we pray thee hide not from us</l>
                  <l>The very cauſe why this is come upon us,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt wee're brought into an exigent</l>
                  <l>And till we know the cauſe are not content;</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou a calling, then what calling haſt?</l>
                  <l>Art thou not one that wilfully doth waſt</l>
                  <l>Thy precious time and live in idleneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And for that ſin ere brought unto diſtreſſe?</l>
                  <l>What is the country now from which thou came?</l>
                  <l>And of what people art tell us by name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now danger great had opend <hi>Ionah's</hi> eyes</l>
                  <l>Therefore he ſays to them in humble wiſe</l>
                  <l>as for my nation it is of the Jews</l>
                  <l>Diſtinct from others by the name Hebrews;</l>
                  <l>I am an hebrew from the loyns deſcended</l>
                  <l>Of him that was of God ſo much befreinded.</l>
                  <l>As for Religion I do fear the Lord,</l>
                  <l>And worſhip him who by his powerful word,</l>
                  <l>Did frame and faſh'on both ſea and dry land,</l>
                  <l>That governs all things at his own command:</l>
                  <l>To God alone and t'none elſe am I bound,</l>
                  <l>Yet at this time in baſe rebellion found.</l>
                  <l>When men are brought into ſome great diſtreſs</l>
                  <l>Though not before yet then they will confeſs</l>
                  <l>Their evil deeds,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of God and his rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</note> the hearts that ſtubborn were</l>
                  <l>Are bruis'd and broken in a time of fear;</l>
                  <l>God in his wiſdome, often thinks it fit</l>
                  <l>To whip a frantick perſon into's wit,</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104634:25"/>
                  <l>And ſure, at ſuch a time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ells his beſt</l>
                  <l>To uſe and to improve what intereſt</l>
                  <l>He hath in God, if any ſuch thing be,</l>
                  <l>And to his uprightneſs for comfort flee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then were the men afraid, with greater fear</l>
                  <l>When ſo much of the true God they do hear,</l>
                  <l>And ſee for ſin he doth due vengeance take</l>
                  <l>And will not ſpare it for a prophets ſake;</l>
                  <l>Then did they ſay, why haſt thou done this thing?</l>
                  <l>How dar'ſt thou diſobey thy Lord and King?</l>
                  <l>What couldſt thou turn away, when he ſays go?</l>
                  <l>Dare you profeſſing Hebrews once do ſo?</l>
                  <l>What fond conceit poſſeſt thee, didſt thou think</l>
                  <l>That for ſo great a fault thy God would wink?</l>
                  <l>For he had told them, and thereby they knew</l>
                  <l>That from the preſence of the Lord he flew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus he that diſobeyed Gods command</l>
                  <l>Doth now convict, condemn'd,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the heathens reprehending <hi>Jonah.</hi>
                     </note> and cenſur'd ſtand</l>
                  <l>Among, and by the barb'rous heathen crue</l>
                  <l>In ſilent wiſe account it all his due;</l>
                  <l>So every one that feareth not Gods name</l>
                  <l>One time or other he will clothe with ſhame</l>
                  <l>And make them ſtand as men all in a maze</l>
                  <l>Dumb like a ſtock on which others do gaze;</l>
                  <l>And by the words of others are reproved</l>
                  <l>Cauſe by the words of God they were not moved:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Seamen ſay <hi>Jona</hi> thou haſt undone us</l>
                  <l>The ſeas ſtill rage and tempeſt lyes upon us,</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls are fill'd with dreadful fears and care</l>
                  <l>And ſtill encreaſing as the tempeſts are;</l>
                  <l>The lot's faln on thee, conſcience tells thee too</l>
                  <l>Thou art the man that doth us quite undo;</l>
                  <l>By which two things thou plainly art detected</l>
                  <l>To be the cauſe yet let us be directed</l>
                  <l>What we ſhall do unto thee that the ſeas</l>
                  <l>May rage and foam no more and winds may ceaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>Iona</hi> anſwered, 'tis not you but I</l>
                  <l>That have provoked God ſo mightily</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104634:25"/>
                  <l>'Tis for my ſake not yours the ſeas are raging</l>
                  <l>And tempeſt ſtill is on you not aſſwaging:</l>
                  <l>Now take me up and caſt me overboard</l>
                  <l>For that's appoynted for me of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>That is the ſentence, I muſt undergo it</l>
                  <l>And ſilently ſubmit my ſelf unto it;</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall there be a calme upon the main</l>
                  <l>And boyſtrous waves ſhall ſmoothly glide again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though God in juſtice ſeem to be ſevere</l>
                  <l>And ſtrict in puniſhing for ſin:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſo patiently ſubmitting to Gods will: accepting the puniſhment of his iniquity.</note> yet here</l>
                  <l>A gratious ſoul ſubmits in any wiſe</l>
                  <l>And ſuffers not one grudging thought to riſe</l>
                  <l>Againſt Gods dealing ſo: but will ſubmit</l>
                  <l>Knowing his ſin is the juſt cauſe of it:</l>
                  <l>For to excuſe himſelf he will not do</l>
                  <l>But ſay, 'tis righteous Lord, that thou doſt ſo:</l>
                  <l>Hee'l take unto himſelf deſerved ſhame</l>
                  <l>Thereby to honour Gods moſt glorious name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come take a view how theſe rude heathen men</l>
                  <l>Behav'd themſelves in love to <hi>Jonah;</hi> when</l>
                  <l>They ſaw his patience, and did hear his word</l>
                  <l>And knew he was a prophet of the Lord;</l>
                  <l>Sure greater love then theirs could not be ſhown</l>
                  <l>They ſeek to ſave his life dang'ring their own,</l>
                  <l>They fain would ſave him, and therefore they try</l>
                  <l>The beſt of means and skill before he dye:</l>
                  <l>They row full hard; now each man lays his hand</l>
                  <l>To work: thinking to bring the ſhip to land</l>
                  <l>They toyl, they ſweat, they labour in great pain</l>
                  <l>And when th'ave done their labor's all in vain.</l>
                  <l>For now as though the elements conſpire</l>
                  <l>To vex them ſtill: the waves they mount up higher</l>
                  <l>The ſea ſtill works, the windy tempeſts roar</l>
                  <l>The ſea-men ceaſe there rowing and give ore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From hence we ſee that a meer humane ſoul</l>
                  <l>Hath ſo much pitty others to condole</l>
                  <l>That God of nature,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the heathen mens endeavour to have ſav'd <hi>Jonah.</hi>
                     </note> ſo much reaſon gave</l>
                  <l>To teach one man anothers life to ſave;</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104634:26"/>
                  <l>More when a beam divine hath influence</l>
                  <l>On them: they give the greater reverence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe men that worſhipt idol gods before</l>
                  <l>Have quickly learn'd the true God to adore;</l>
                  <l>And now like unto new converted Saints</l>
                  <l>They go to God alone, with prayer and plants:</l>
                  <l>And leſt the guilt of blood ſhould on them ly,</l>
                  <l>They make to heaven and liſt up their cry.</l>
                  <l>We do beſeech thee Lord deſtroy us not</l>
                  <l>For this mans ſake: but leave us without ſpot:</l>
                  <l>We do beſeech thee Lord, and humbly pray;</l>
                  <l>Blood innocent on us thou wilt not lay,</l>
                  <l>For we perceive Lord that it is thy will,</l>
                  <l>And we as executioners do fulfill</l>
                  <l>Even as thy bleſſed pleaſure hath deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>For all is done according to thy mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Men in affliction earneſtly will cry,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the heathen mens addreſſing themſelves to God in this ſtrait.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The worſt of men then unto God will fly</l>
                  <l>Self guides the ſtern ofttimes, and beareth ſway;</l>
                  <l>For love to ſelf and not to God; they'le pray:</l>
                  <l>But every one that is a convert true,</l>
                  <l>In every ſeaſon yeildeth God his due,</l>
                  <l>Unto his God he prays, to him he'l cry,</l>
                  <l>Not only when afflictions on him lye,</l>
                  <l>And when ſome difficultys ſtand before,</l>
                  <l>But when all ſuch with eaſe he can get ore:</l>
                  <l>If this or that befall, he's mov'd by neither,</l>
                  <l>Hee'l pray as well in fair as fouler weather.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So they took <hi>Jonah</hi> as it pleas'd the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Into the ſea they caſt him overboard,</l>
                  <l>Whereat the ſea it ſeem'd well ſatisfy'd</l>
                  <l>The ſtormy tempeſt now is layd aſide:</l>
                  <l>No token of diſpleaſure now appears</l>
                  <l>Nor nothing ſeen to uſher future fears;</l>
                  <l>Now all is done, even as the Lord did pleaſe</l>
                  <l>His anger now is calme: ſo are the ſeas.</l>
                  <l>If judgment at Gods houſe do firſt begin,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his own ſervant.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And God not wink, though at a prophets ſin:</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104634:26"/>
                  <l>If God his deareſt ones he will not ſpare</l>
                  <l>But they of this and t'other ſtripe muſt ſhare,</l>
                  <l>As God in juſtice pleaſeth to paſs ſentence,</l>
                  <l>Then thoſe ungodly ones without repentance</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fearleſs graceleſs wicked wretches; who</l>
                  <l>From one rebellion to another go;</l>
                  <l>The devils drudges, driving on ſins trade</l>
                  <l>Muſt pay full dear for it; when th'reckoning's made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſeamen ſeeing all things that had paſt</l>
                  <l>They cannot chuſe but ſtand like men agaſt</l>
                  <l>They caſt off idols; greatly fear the Lord,</l>
                  <l>And offer ſacrifice, while yet aboard:</l>
                  <l>And leſt theſe wonders, ſhould ſlip out of mind</l>
                  <l>Themſelves by vows and oaths full faſt they bind,</l>
                  <l>To praiſe the Lord that ſav'd them from the deep</l>
                  <l>And all their day's, this vow they mean to keep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When God in wond'rous manner doth appear</l>
                  <l>And to mens ſouls in mercy doth draw near,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the ſea-mens devoting themſelves to God.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When he puts forth his power to touch the heart,</l>
                  <l>Men are made willing from their ſins to part:</l>
                  <l>Till by the fear of God their ſouls are mov'd</l>
                  <l>They will not leave what they ſo long have lov'd:</l>
                  <l>But when Gods power doth form a creature new</l>
                  <l>The divel, world and fleſh they bid adieu;</l>
                  <l>They break their bonds with them that tied them faſt</l>
                  <l>And cleave to God with purpoſes to laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come view the care and providence of God</l>
                  <l>Who though he did chaſtice, with's angry rod</l>
                  <l>Yet mercy ſhews when juſtice might take place</l>
                  <l>And after frowns, ſhews forth a pleaſant face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now to ſatisfy his love and care</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> mighty whale before hand did prepare,</l>
                  <l>For to devour and in devouring ſave:</l>
                  <l>His belly now it muſt be <hi>Jonah's</hi> grave,</l>
                  <l>In which dark vault the Lord did him imbarque</l>
                  <l>Three days and nights, as ſafe as in an arke</l>
                  <l>Where deaths black terrors do ſurround his ſoul</l>
                  <l>His paſſing bell in's eare doth always toul</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:104634:27"/>
                  <l>Where now we leave him, thus begirt with fear</l>
                  <l>Till in another wonder God appear.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>How <hi>Jonah</hi> unto God did pray</l>
                  <l>Now he is in his grave</l>
                  <l>God heard, and in a wondrous way</l>
                  <l>How he did <hi>Jonah</hi> ſave.</l>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw ſee how good afflictions often prove</l>
                  <l>They are not only tokens of Gods love,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement by his affliction.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sins paſt correct, and future ſins prevent</l>
                  <l>But for ſome other cauſes they are ſent,</l>
                  <l>The wandring roving ſteps for to bring back</l>
                  <l>And quicken ſouls to dutyes, that are ſlack.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Jona</hi> in the depth of miſery</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeks not God in time of liberty</l>
                  <l>But runs and flees, and hides him from his face</l>
                  <l>Doth now cry to him in this diſmal caſe,</l>
                  <l>He now is caſt into deaths darkſome bed</l>
                  <l>Its ſable curtains wrap about his head,</l>
                  <l>The king of terrour, terrible appears</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Jonah's</hi> heart, doth melt away with fears,</l>
                  <l>Out of the fiſhes belly <hi>Jonah's</hi> grave</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jonah</hi> had hope that God would <hi>Jonah</hi> ſave,</l>
                  <l>His faith begetteth prayer; he prays in faith</l>
                  <l>And to the Lord his God theſe words he ſaith</l>
                  <l>When faith gets ſtrength, and hope takes ancor hold</l>
                  <l>The ſoul that feard before, doth now grow bold</l>
                  <l>With great and greivous troubles being preſt,</l>
                  <l>He knocks at heavens gates and will not reſt</l>
                  <l>Until his ſuit do finde acceptance there</l>
                  <l>And gracious anſwer be return'd to prayer;</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104634:27"/>
                  <l>Hee'l ſeek, hee'l ſue, hee'l cry, and not give ore</l>
                  <l>Till God do open what was ſhut before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord my ſoul is brought into diſtreſs</l>
                  <l>I have deſerv'd it; yet a great deal leſſe</l>
                  <l>Then what I do deſerve I undergo;</l>
                  <l>Thou art a gracious God then mercy ſhow;</l>
                  <l>'Twas my affliction great that made me cry</l>
                  <l>And 'twas thy mercy t'hear ſo ſpeedily</l>
                  <l>My earneſt ſute, thou didſt it not ſay nay</l>
                  <l>When I out of this helliſh grave did pray:</l>
                  <l>Thou heardeſt me, when I thy face had ſought</l>
                  <l>And thou haſt for me great ſalvation wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No labor's loſt when we are in diſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>To make to heaven by humble addreſſe</l>
                  <l>With hearts all melting,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Jonah</hi> had in turning cleaning to God in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</note> broken and contrite</l>
                  <l>A thing in which God takes ſo much delight,</l>
                  <l>When in this frame of ſpirit we make ſute,</l>
                  <l>To God alone in Chriſt, then that will do't,</l>
                  <l>When we confeſſe our ſins with grief and ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And do reform our lives the fleſh to tame</l>
                  <l>Such bleſt endeavours, never proves in vain,</l>
                  <l>Though God were gone; it brings him back again.</l>
                  <l>'Twas not the ſeamen but it was the Lord</l>
                  <l>That took me up, and caſt me overboard</l>
                  <l>They did fulfil even as thou Lord didſt pleaſe</l>
                  <l>'Twas thou by them, caſt me into the ſeas</l>
                  <l>Into the midſt and heart of them: where thoſe</l>
                  <l>Proud waters did me ſecretly incloſe</l>
                  <l>The floods the ſeas, rais'd high with winde and tide</l>
                  <l>They do encompaſs me on every ſide</l>
                  <l>All thy proud billows, which do mount on high</l>
                  <l>At thy command: yet elſe do ſmoothly lye,</l>
                  <l>And towring waves which I poor fool alas!</l>
                  <l>Thought to get ore: yet now all ore me paſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When gracious ſouls are brought under the rod</l>
                  <l>That is i'th hand of a diſpleaſed God,<note place="margin">Obſervation from <hi>Jonah's</hi> looking at the hand of the Lord and not at the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be made uſe of.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor this, nor that, who is the inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>But God they eye, who hath affliction ſent,</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104634:28"/>
                  <l>Not like the dog, that gnawing is the ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Regarding not the hand, by which its thrown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And then I ſaid, for I was in great fear</l>
                  <l>And lab'ring was, betwixt hope and deſpair,</l>
                  <l>(The darkneſſe having dim'd the cleareſt light)</l>
                  <l>Then ſaid I, Lord I'm caſt out of thy ſight;</l>
                  <l>Yet notwithſtanding, all the grace thou haſt,</l>
                  <l>Seemeth to me, as if 'twere lockt up faſt</l>
                  <l>And that no beam of light <hi>I</hi> can eſpy,</l>
                  <l>Yet will I look again with ſtedfaſt eye</l>
                  <l>Toward thy temple, and that holy place,</l>
                  <l>Where Lord thou promiſt haſt, to ſhew thy face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Two contraries are in the beſt of men</l>
                  <l>The party vanquiſht,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from the warr be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the fleſh and ſpirit in the beſt.</note> fain would riſe again</l>
                  <l>The fleſh and ſpirit, do oppoſe each other,</l>
                  <l>The elder's loth to ſerve the younger brother</l>
                  <l>Great conteſtation is twixt faith and doubt</l>
                  <l>Hopeleſs deſpair, ſtrives hard true faith to rout</l>
                  <l>Theſe two opponents bicker in the feild</l>
                  <l>Nor one nor other of theſe two will yeild</l>
                  <l>Till faith puts forth at laſt, and ſtriketh home</l>
                  <l>With blows, that doubting fear do overcome;</l>
                  <l>A man thats brought into a woful ſtate</l>
                  <l>Will oftentimes his miſery relate</l>
                  <l>And will enlarge himſelf to tell his grief</l>
                  <l>Thinking by telling it, to finde relief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So <hi>Jonah</hi> does his miſery repeat</l>
                  <l>And ſays the water's plentiful and great,</l>
                  <l>They did inviron me they did me wrap</l>
                  <l>As ſwadling bands the babe in mothers lap;</l>
                  <l>Three days and nights they do about me roul,</l>
                  <l>And deaths black herſe encompaſſes my ſoul:</l>
                  <l>The waters deep were dayly ore me ſpread,</l>
                  <l>And ſtinking weeds did wrap about my head:</l>
                  <l>Unto the bottome of the mountains ſteep,</l>
                  <l>Then I went down ſtill fathoming the deep</l>
                  <l>Sometimes I was aloft upon the main,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon plungd down into the depths again:</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104634:28"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> was in priſon and the earth did barr me</l>
                  <l>And horrid fears, do every minute ſcar-me,</l>
                  <l>For ever hopeleſs to ſet foot on ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe thou by a wonder me reſtore:</l>
                  <l>Yet thou O Lord my God, was pleas'd to ſave</l>
                  <l>And brought my life again up from the grave,</l>
                  <l>That cruel corrupt loathſome ſtinking pit</l>
                  <l>Where death had almoſt ſwallow'd me in it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There's no condition that can be ſo ſad,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining deliverance and his thankfulneſſe for the ſame.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor ſtate of man that ever was ſo bad,</l>
                  <l>There is no burden can ſo heavy lye</l>
                  <l>Nor vexing grief nor preſſing miſery,</l>
                  <l>But God almighty by his mighty ſtrength</l>
                  <l>He can deliver: and he will at length</l>
                  <l>Deliver thoſe that do on him rely,</l>
                  <l>And pray to him in faith with earneſt cry;</l>
                  <l>From their low ſtate he can and will them raiſe</l>
                  <l>And when 'tis done they'l ever give him praiſe;</l>
                  <l>They will confeſs that he ſalvation wrought,</l>
                  <l>And heard as ſoon, as they his face had ſought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When my heart broke and ſoul it fainting lay</l>
                  <l>To eaſe my ſelf I could deviſe no way,</l>
                  <l>My thoughts to this and then to that were led,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill they did return upon my head;</l>
                  <l>Then did I think upon (for it was time),</l>
                  <l>The mercys Lord thou ever haſt ſhewn thine,</l>
                  <l>My hope was ancor, and it took faſt hold</l>
                  <l>And to the throne of grace now I make bold,</l>
                  <l>My humble prayer for to preſent to thee,</l>
                  <l>Though like a rebell lately I fled from thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt not ſhut it out: (oh wondrous grace)</l>
                  <l>But it came in, unto thy holy place.<note place="margin">Obſerva. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coraging himſelf to rely on God and cry to him from conſideration of former mercys.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When we poor creatures know not what to do</l>
                  <l>To one ſhift and another are put to,</l>
                  <l>And find no means of help to avoid our trouble</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of help, they are returned double:</l>
                  <l>When every veſſel leaks and refuge fails,</l>
                  <l>And every hold we have nothing avails:</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104634:29"/>
                  <l>When each proud wave and billow doth paſs ore-us</l>
                  <l>And death with all his terror ſtand before-us,</l>
                  <l>Then it is time, full time to call to minde,</l>
                  <l>Each thing of God, that we did ever finde</l>
                  <l>To ſtrengthen faith and give encouragement</l>
                  <l>Our prayers in heavens court for to preſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All ye that hunt and follow after lies</l>
                  <l>And are obſerving idle vanities</l>
                  <l>That have dependency on falſe deceits</l>
                  <l>That evermore the ſilly ſinner cheats</l>
                  <l>As long as ye theſe ſinfull courſes take</l>
                  <l>In chooſing theſe; your own mercys forſake</l>
                  <l>Both preſent happineſs and future bliſs</l>
                  <l>And I by ſad experience tell you this.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe that at any time have gone aſtray</l>
                  <l>Turning aſide out of Gods holy way</l>
                  <l>And are whipt for it till their backs do bleed,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving warning to others from woful experience.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can beſt of all warn others to take heed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now as for thoſe that follow vanities</l>
                  <l>And unto idol-gods do ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>Aſcribing to them each deliverance</l>
                  <l>Accounting all things as they came by chance,</l>
                  <l>Both th'one and th'other always come to naught,</l>
                  <l>But as for my part I am better taught,</l>
                  <l>And unto thee O Lord my heart will raiſe</l>
                  <l>And ſacrifice unto thy name with praiſe;</l>
                  <l>I will give thanks unto thy holy name</l>
                  <l>From thee and none elſe my deliverance came,</l>
                  <l>And now I'le pay to thee that I have vowed,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I know by thee I am allowed;</l>
                  <l>For why I know ther's no ſalvation wrought,</l>
                  <l>But what thy hand, O Lord to paſs hath brought.<note place="margin">Obſerva. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> thankfulneſs for his delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When God appears to us in love and grace</l>
                  <l>And ſhews again the beauty of his face</l>
                  <l>When he unfolds his armes to let us in,</l>
                  <l>And draws a mantle ore to hide our ſin,</l>
                  <l>When he puts forth his power not to deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>But ſave; and fill our hearts with perfect joy,</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104634:29"/>
                  <l>Surely it is an obligation ſtrong</l>
                  <l>To binde our hearts: but ſo unlooſe our tongue</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak in praiſe, talking t'others abroad</l>
                  <l>'Oth wiſdome, goodneſs, mercy, power of God;</l>
                  <l>But when his grace is turn'd to wantonneſs</l>
                  <l>And mercy move men neither more nor leſſe,</l>
                  <l>Lives to reform and manners to amend</l>
                  <l>Thoſe mercys turn to judgments in the end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſpake the Lord that hath the ſole command</l>
                  <l>Of all the crearures in the ſea and land</l>
                  <l>He ſpake unto the whale within the ſea</l>
                  <l>The whale no ſooner heard but did obey,</l>
                  <l>He ſaid to him, <hi>Jonah</hi> I mean to ſave,</l>
                  <l>Thy belly hath been long enough his grave</l>
                  <l>My mighty power, now he ſhall underſtand</l>
                  <l>Therefore go bring him quickly to the land;</l>
                  <l>Then did the fiſh launch forrh, away he went</l>
                  <l>Unto the place whether the Lord him ſent,</l>
                  <l>He ſplits the ſeas with haſt until they roar</l>
                  <l>And vomits <hi>Jonah</hi> ſafely on the ſhore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſhall a fiſh that in the ſeas doth dwell</l>
                  <l>Hear and obey Gods voice and not rebel,<note place="margin">Obſerva. from the whales obedience to Gods command.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>One void of reaſon and religion too,</l>
                  <l>At the firſt bidding; as God bids him do.</l>
                  <l>God ſpeaks but once unto the mighty whale</l>
                  <l>At his command he ſtops: then hearken all</l>
                  <l>To whom God ſpeaks not only once nor twice</l>
                  <l>But ore and ore he comes with new ſupplys</l>
                  <l>Of precepts mingled, with entreatiſe dear,</l>
                  <l>To ſtir them up his holy name to fear,</l>
                  <l>Crying aloud, Oh do this thing and live,</l>
                  <l>But yet for all that, no attendance give.</l>
                  <l>Shall th' queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> travail from the ſouth</l>
                  <l>To hear the wiſdome, dropping from the mouth</l>
                  <l>Of a meer man; ſhall <hi>Niniveh</hi> repent,</l>
                  <l>As ſoon as <hi>Jonah</hi> unto them was ſent,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Sheba's</hi> queen the Ninivites and whale</l>
                  <l>Shall riſe in judgment, and condemn them all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104634:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>How <hi>Jonah</hi> unto <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niveh</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A ſ cond time is ſent</l>
                  <l>They heare: in hearing do obey</l>
                  <l>The Lord did then repent.</l>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>NO ſooner were all theſe things done and paſt</l>
                  <l>But God his mercy (which doth ever laſt)</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Jonah</hi> ſhews:<note place="margin">Obſerva. from the prophets declaring that and only that the Lord commanded him &amp; not going before the Lord ſent him.</note> to grace he doth receive him</l>
                  <l>And though he did provoke he will not leave him.</l>
                  <l>Though from his office he might be degraded</l>
                  <l>Yet for his fault, he is not now upbraded.</l>
                  <l>But now a ſecond time their comes a word</l>
                  <l>Sent unto <hi>Jonah</hi> from the higheſt Lord</l>
                  <l>Saying ariſe, begone and do not ſtay</l>
                  <l>Mine anger will ariſe, if thou delay</l>
                  <l>Thou art commanded make no more excuſes</l>
                  <l>Know thou my patience brooks no more abuſes.</l>
                  <l>Unto that famous City <hi>Niniveh</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I again ſend thee and ſee that thou ſay</l>
                  <l>The word I bid thee, when thou comeſt there</l>
                  <l>Preach that, whether they heare or do forbear.</l>
                  <l>And though of thee not one would have regard</l>
                  <l>And for ſuch news canſt look for no reward,</l>
                  <l>Yet be thou ſtrong, take courage, ſee thou do it,</l>
                  <l>I charge thee turn not off, but go unto it.</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd of this, and they ſhall know</l>
                  <l>That within forty days i'le overthrow</l>
                  <l>Their City great, if they within that ſpace</l>
                  <l>Do not repent that I may ſhew them grace.</l>
                  <l>All thoſe that run when God ſays no ſuch thing,</l>
                  <l>Not God but their own errand they will bring,</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104634:30"/>
                  <l>The meſſage God commands they'l not impart</l>
                  <l>But what's devis'd in their own fooliſh heart,</l>
                  <l>Or that which man commands, with zeal they preſſe</l>
                  <l>But what God bids them preach: a great deal leſs</l>
                  <l>Of care and zeal they ſpend; which doth declare</l>
                  <l>That not the true but prophets falſe they are:</l>
                  <l>But hee's the prophet true goes not before</l>
                  <l>God ſend him furniſht with a heavenly ſtore</l>
                  <l>What he commands him ſtill he keeps to that,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak and do; regardleſs always what</l>
                  <l>Men do oppoſe, nor love nor fear that draws him</l>
                  <l>To fail his truſt; for'ts love and fear that aws him.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jonah</hi> doth ariſe away he gets</l>
                  <l>And toward <hi>Niniveh</hi> his face he ſets,</l>
                  <l>He trudges on, regards not wind nor weather,</l>
                  <l>Nor takes not up his reſt till he come thither;</l>
                  <l>For God had ſtrictly charg'd him by his word</l>
                  <l>And now his care is therewith to accord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Men for their ſins do often feel the rod</l>
                  <l>And heavy hand of a diſpleaſed God,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting now to perform what God gave him in charge.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before affliction comes they go aſtray</l>
                  <l>But learn by it their maſter to obey.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now this ſame great Aſſirian city where</l>
                  <l>The prophet with his ſermon muſt appear,</l>
                  <l>It was exceeding great, greater then other,</l>
                  <l>And of all cities well might be the mother;</l>
                  <l>It was ſo long, ſo broad, ſpacious and wide,</l>
                  <l>Three days to travail it from ſide to ſide</l>
                  <l>Might be a journey for a man moſt fit,</l>
                  <l>For ſo recorded 'tis in holy writ.</l>
                  <l>Beſides ſome ſay, that humane hiſtories</l>
                  <l>Do make report, ſome ſay they are not lies,</l>
                  <l>That threeſcore miles would but this city round,</l>
                  <l>And fifteen hundred towrs in it were found;</l>
                  <l>The walls in height, full thirty yards and more,</l>
                  <l>The like was ſurely never ſeen before;</l>
                  <l>The bredth o'th walls was equal to the reſt</l>
                  <l>They ſay two chariots might well paſs in breſt,</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104634:31"/>
                  <l>And ſpace enough for divers left between,</l>
                  <l>Such walls in height and breadth beſides, nere ſeen</l>
                  <l>And ſixſcore thouſand infants were found there,</l>
                  <l>As the next chapter makes it to appear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unto this city mighty and of fame</l>
                  <l>At laſt full tir'd and weary <hi>Ionah</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>Paſſes the ſtreets one day, begins to thunder</l>
                  <l>Out his unwelcome news: makes them to wonder</l>
                  <l>And ſtand like men afright, with gaſtly fear,</l>
                  <l>Their ears do tingle at the news they hear;</l>
                  <l>With fainting fits th'are ready to drop down,</l>
                  <l>Each tells another news thats come to town.</l>
                  <l>All thus alarm'd they ſtand as in a maze</l>
                  <l>And every one at other ſeems to gaze;</l>
                  <l>The larum runs apace through every ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>And all that hear tell others whom they meet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For <hi>Jonah</hi> went along with dolefull cry</l>
                  <l>Yet fourty days and then God will deſtroy</l>
                  <l>This city great, then he will overthrow it</l>
                  <l>And charg'd me ſtraitly unto you to ſhow it,</l>
                  <l>To threaten you with judgment I was ſent</l>
                  <l>My errand I have ſaid, repent, repent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that a hand appear but on the wall</l>
                  <l>Debaucht <hi>Belſhazers</hi> countenance will fall</l>
                  <l>His joynts unlooſe, his knees together daſh:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the Ninivits diſponding as the judgment threatned by <hi>Jonah.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When God puts forth his rod to ſcourge and ſlaſh.</l>
                  <l>Oppreſſing <hi>Pharoahs</hi> heart, it will come down</l>
                  <l>When God in ferious manner 'gins to frown.</l>
                  <l>Let churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> hear what might come on,</l>
                  <l>His heart within him's cold like to a ſtone.</l>
                  <l>The proud and lofty Ninivites do fear</l>
                  <l>When God in threatned wrath doth but appear.</l>
                  <l>The wicked, great, proud perſecuting ones</l>
                  <l>That naught regard the poor mans ſighs and groans,</l>
                  <l>If God come forth and beare his powerfull arme</l>
                  <l>And cauſe his trumpet, give them one alarm,</l>
                  <l>When time is not and judgment cannot ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Their hearts do faint, and fainting melt away</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104634:31"/>
                  <l>Much more proud wretches when they once do feel</l>
                  <l>The force and ſmart of his ſharp-glitt'ring ſteel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Ninivits no ſooner heard the word</l>
                  <l>And dreadfull judgments threatned by the Lord,</l>
                  <l>But they believe him and think he had ſent</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jonah</hi> to warn each perſon to repent.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore they do agree with one accord</l>
                  <l>To turn from ſin unto the living Lord:</l>
                  <l>And to prepare them fitly for the ſame</l>
                  <l>A Solemn faſt the people do proclame;</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſant food they will not now partake</l>
                  <l>Their joviall feaſting they do now forſake;</l>
                  <l>Of dainty delicates they taſt no more</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of mirth and muſick now they roar:</l>
                  <l>Each face grows pale, and blackneſs now doth gather</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of play and ſports now they had rather</l>
                  <l>Sit in the duſt; with heavy ſighs and groans</l>
                  <l>And tears in eyes to heaven making moans:</l>
                  <l>Their brave attire, and gorgeous rich aray</l>
                  <l>In which they proudly deckt themſelves each day</l>
                  <l>Their broydred ſhining garments: and ſuch things</l>
                  <l>As hoods and cauls their jewels and their rings</l>
                  <l>Are layd aſide by all; and there is none</l>
                  <l>That doth adventure now to put them on.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead whereof they put duſt on their head</l>
                  <l>And ſackcloth on each perſon now is ſpread</l>
                  <l>Wherewith to cloath themſelves now they think fit</l>
                  <l>And all in ſable wiſe in aſhes ſit.</l>
                  <l>Their eyes diſtill; their cheeks are wet with tears</l>
                  <l>And hearts no doubt, are ſwallowed up with fears.</l>
                  <l>when <hi>Jona</hi> had ſcarce three days mongſt them taught</l>
                  <l>His ſermons on them wonderfully wrought,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the Ninivits believing <hi>Jonah</hi> and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>May be he preacht three years in <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And's Sermons never wrought on them ſo well</l>
                  <l>when God puts forth his power mens hearts to reach</l>
                  <l>They ſoon are toucht with what his prophets preach</l>
                  <l>And when they lye under a fearfull ſentence</l>
                  <l>O then or never they fall to repentance,</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104634:32"/>
                  <l>And then great preſent changes will be found</l>
                  <l>Yet ſuch repentances ate ſeldome ſound</l>
                  <l>When men repent for fear or ſmart o'th rod</l>
                  <l>Tis more for love to ſelf, then love to God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner did this news arive at court</l>
                  <l>But then their king leaves of his princly ſport,</l>
                  <l>This mighty monarch glorious and high</l>
                  <l>Deſcends the throne of his great majeſty.</l>
                  <l>His golden chayne and kingly robe ſo royall</l>
                  <l>He now puts off and puts on ſelf deniall,</l>
                  <l>He rents his cloaths: and ſits in aſhes too</l>
                  <l>And now the king doth as his ſubjects do.</l>
                  <l>In heavy ſackcloath he is humbly dreſt</l>
                  <l>Expreſſing grief thereby, as do the reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This heathen king,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the heathens kings patient reception of <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſad tidings.</note> takes all full patiently</l>
                  <l>Though judgment judgment ſtill was <hi>Ionah's</hi> cry,</l>
                  <l>He neither frets nor fumes, nor rails nor rages</l>
                  <l>As others that have liv'd in clearer ages</l>
                  <l>Who would impriſon him that tidings brought</l>
                  <l>Of their deſtruction, but he's better taught;</l>
                  <l>May all in power and place learn to ſubmit</l>
                  <l>And hear the rod, and him that 'pointed it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now with conſent of all his nobles great</l>
                  <l>That do attend upon his royall ſeat</l>
                  <l>His privy Counſel great Aſſirian Lords;</l>
                  <l>With whom in this ſad junto he accords.</l>
                  <l>Be it enacted let it be decreed,</l>
                  <l>That from this time not any one do feed</l>
                  <l>On any thing their natures do ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>But from all kind of food they do refrain;</l>
                  <l>Our pleaſure is nor good nor bad they taſt,</l>
                  <l>So long as this our royall act doth laſt:</l>
                  <l>Let all take notice both the great and leaſt;</l>
                  <l>Not men alone we ſay but every beaſt,</l>
                  <l>And flock and heard that grazeth in the feild,</l>
                  <l>To gain the ſuccour graſs and herbs do yield;</l>
                  <l>Shall taſt no food nor water drink no more</l>
                  <l>Untill for pining want each beaſt doth roar.</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104634:32"/>
                  <l>With bellowing cry: that they may us excite</l>
                  <l>To lay aſide all pleaſures and delight</l>
                  <l>To weep and wayle, and mournfully lament</l>
                  <l>Thereby to ſignify we do repent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O what is ſin ſo much to be abhor'd,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from not only ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man repenting but the beaſts of the feild mourning alſo.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>O it is ſin ſo much provoks the Lord</l>
                  <l>To puniſh man and beaſt; not man alone</l>
                  <l>But for the ſins of men the creatures groane.</l>
                  <l>The ſinleſs beaſt, nor need, nor can repent</l>
                  <l>Yet with the ſinner, needs they muſt lament:</l>
                  <l>May ſinful man ſtand then all in a maze,</l>
                  <l>When on the ſinleſs creature he doth gaze;</l>
                  <l>Groaning with grief; for the juſt God therein</l>
                  <l>Shews how he is diſpleas'd with men for ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And further by the foreſaid thority</l>
                  <l>We do decree; and to all ſignify</l>
                  <l>That every man put off his rich aray,</l>
                  <l>And every beaſt, his ornaments this day,</l>
                  <l>This darkſome day, wherein none can be glad</l>
                  <l>Let man and beaſt in ſackcloath rough be clad;</l>
                  <l>And while that all thus ſadly mourning ly,</l>
                  <l>Let every one to God lift up his cry</l>
                  <l>With earneſt powerful prayers, now make your ſuit</l>
                  <l>For weak, nor feigned prayers now will not do't<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſins we have diſpleaſed God on high</l>
                  <l>And if he ſhew not mercy we muſt dy,</l>
                  <l>We guilty are of many great offence,</l>
                  <l>And moſt of all we have us'd violence</l>
                  <l>Within this city; it cleaves to our hands</l>
                  <l>Let's clenſe our ſelves from it now he commands,</l>
                  <l>And with our prayers &amp; tears &amp; outward mourning</l>
                  <l>Let every of us from our ſins be turning.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thus by king and Counſel 'twas decreed</l>
                  <l>Signed and ſeal'd,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree for repentance and haſt to the execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> it haſts with winged ſpeed</l>
                  <l>It flys abroad and runs through every ſtreet</l>
                  <l>Each tels another of it whom they meet,</l>
                  <l>For why it was proclaimed in his name</l>
                  <l>And heralds fit to execute the ſame;</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104634:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104634:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104634:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104634:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104634:35"/>
                  <l>Where true repentance gods there goes confeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Repentance true, nere goes without contrition;</l>
                  <l>Self judging too, repentance doth call in</l>
                  <l>Whereby t'eſcape Gods judgments due for ſin;</l>
                  <l>Unfained prayer doth aſſiſtance lend,</l>
                  <l>And reformation life for to amend,</l>
                  <l>For where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mendment, joyns with hearty grief</l>
                  <l>Hope may be had that it will bring relief.</l>
                  <l>And cary'd on with ſtrength of reſolution</l>
                  <l>To ſpend and haſt the work to execution;</l>
                  <l>The penitent he can no longer ſtay</l>
                  <l>But meets an angry God half on his way,</l>
                  <l>When God againſt him comes tho's pace be flack</l>
                  <l>He mends his pace, and runs to turn him back.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now behold what mov'd this heathen king</l>
                  <l>To conſtitute, ordain, appoint this thing,</l>
                  <l>It was not only thoughts of preſent fear</l>
                  <l>But God in mercy alſo might appear,</l>
                  <l>For who can tell, ſayth he, or who doth know,</l>
                  <l>Whether this city he will overthrow</l>
                  <l>If we perſiſt not on but do repent;</l>
                  <l>May be for this end <hi>Jona</hi> he was ſent;</l>
                  <l>Perhaps returning, we ſhall mercy finde</l>
                  <l>For I have heard to mercy hee's inclin'd;</l>
                  <l>We do not know therefore let us make tryal,</l>
                  <l>But if we turn from ſin and be found loyal,</l>
                  <l>But God may turn away from his feirce wrath</l>
                  <l>And will repent of what the prophet hath</l>
                  <l>Pronounc'd againſt us that we may not dy,</l>
                  <l>Although he ſays that he will us deſtroy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gods mercys great,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the Niniv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s encouragement to turn of to God, becauſe he is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull God.</note> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> found</l>
                  <l>Good ancre-hold for ſouls: hopes ſureſt ground;</l>
                  <l>Poor ſinner; when at loſs, then do make bold</l>
                  <l>To graſpe at mercy and there take faſt-hold</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oul to ſave from horrid deſperation,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> get a bleſſed expectation:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> means for to eſcape the fire</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nkindled wrath and burning ire)</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:104634:35"/>
                  <l>Mercy to finde: yet 'tis but peradventur</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul had waſted all thy mercy lent-her,</l>
                  <l>And now it's come to this, I do not know</l>
                  <l>Whether I ſhall finde mercy yea or no:</l>
                  <l>What though it be to thee a doubtful thing,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul into the hands of mercy fling,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Concerning <hi>Niniveh</hi> ſee how't appears,</l>
                  <l>Who now ſit mourning all bedew'd with tears,</l>
                  <l>Nor mirth, nor muſick heard; not one is glad,</l>
                  <l>But every one in hairy ſackcloath clad;</l>
                  <l>Yet this is judg'd to be the ſmalleſt part</l>
                  <l>Of works that manifeſt a trve convert:</l>
                  <l>With it they turn'd from all their evil ways</l>
                  <l>God ſaw they did it; and they did him pleaſe</l>
                  <l>For 'tis not ſorrow much nor proteſtation</l>
                  <l>Gainſt ſin that pleaſeth God but reformation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The evils all God ſaid he would do to them</l>
                  <l>Are now remov'd, and turned away from them,</l>
                  <l>They are ſuſpended upon this condition</l>
                  <l>That they amendment joyned with contrition,</l>
                  <l>For the moſt gratious God repents of what</l>
                  <l>He ſaid that he would do, and does it not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great is the force of faith and true repentance</l>
                  <l>Though judgment paſſe,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to puniſh upon their turning to him.</note> it will reverce the ſentence</l>
                  <l>When ſin is left that ſinful ſouls beguiles,</l>
                  <l>Gods frowns are turned into pleaſant ſmiles:</l>
                  <l>His threatned judgments, often are ſuſpended,</l>
                  <l>When as the people threatned are amended.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104634:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>How <hi>Jonah's</hi> angry cauſe the word</l>
                  <l>He preacht had not ſucceſs,</l>
                  <l>As he would have: God by a gourd</l>
                  <l>Reproves his fooliſhneſſe.</l>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>BUt now when <hi>Jona</hi> ſaw the ſtrange event</l>
                  <l>His ſermon had it made him diſcontent</l>
                  <l>He now is angry and doth take diſpleaſure</l>
                  <l>His angers great and doth excel all meaſure;</l>
                  <l>He frets, he pets, he peeviſhly fume o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> blu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cauſe God does not, as he will have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do</l>
                  <l>For God repents; the Sirians ſcapt his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and,</l>
                  <l>And enemies they'l be to Judahs land,</l>
                  <l>May <hi>Jonah</hi> think; and ſo his country men</l>
                  <l>Abundantly had fared better then</l>
                  <l>If they had been deſtroy'd; as was the word</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Jonah</hi> preached to them from the Lord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Blinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eal and carnal ends do oft miſguide</l>
                  <l>The beſt of men and cauſe them turn aſide</l>
                  <l>Time after time:<note place="margin">Obſerv. frow <hi>Jonah</hi>'s b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry at the Lords ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Niniveh.</hi>
                     </note> their luſt they will fulfil</l>
                  <l>If God his actions ſteare not as they will;</l>
                  <l>Self would be ſerv'd whether God will or no,</l>
                  <l>If God ſay yea ſelf never will ſay ſo;</l>
                  <l>Gods will and mans each other oft opoſe,</l>
                  <l>'Tis hard for mans with Gods will for to cloſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What this is ſtrange, a prophet be diſpleas'd</l>
                  <l>That to'ards a people God is now apeas'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſhews them mercy whom he might deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Turning their days of mourning into joy.</l>
                  <l>Can any ſoul but <hi>Jonas</hi> be offended,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of judgment to ſee grace extended?</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104634:36"/>
                  <l>But that's not all: why <hi>Jonah</hi> he is croſt</l>
                  <l>His fame, his name, and honour now is loſt.</l>
                  <l>To be a prophet falſe he is afraid</l>
                  <l>Leſt that among them ſuch a thing be ſaid;</l>
                  <l>And now unto the Lord he doth addreſs</l>
                  <l>Himſelf by prayer that ſignifies no leſs:</l>
                  <l>In it he doth the Lord his God accuſe</l>
                  <l>To be in fault, when as he did refuſe</l>
                  <l>To hear his voice at firſt: and did rebell</l>
                  <l>Pleading as if thereby he had done well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unbridled paſſion is a thing that will</l>
                  <l>Tranſport the ſoul of men ſo long;<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his rebellious fault on God thinking to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> untill</l>
                  <l>God and themſelves they totally forget</l>
                  <l>And go beyond the bounds that reaſon ſet,</l>
                  <l>And reaſonleſs, they fooliſhly will reaſon</l>
                  <l>And think 'tis loyalty, when 'tis but treaſon</l>
                  <l>They think and ſpeak, and act againſt the Lord</l>
                  <l>Such fruits ſelf-love and paſſion do afford.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For this he ſays, I pray thee Lord hear me,</l>
                  <l>While I expoſtulate the caſe with thee;</l>
                  <l>Have I not cauſe to be in angry mood?</l>
                  <l>Was any man ſo ſerv'd that ever ſtood,</l>
                  <l>His credit with thy glory to maintain?</l>
                  <l>If none were ſo then well may I complain.</l>
                  <l>Ere I went out of my own countrey dear,</l>
                  <l>This was the very thing that I did fear:</l>
                  <l>Not only fear it but I ſaid it too,</l>
                  <l>For why? I thought full well what thou wouldſt do:</l>
                  <l>Thou would not bring to paſs what I muſt ſay,</l>
                  <l>And preach and cry aloud at <hi>Niniveh.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I thought full ſure that thou wouldſt ſoon repent</l>
                  <l>Yet to denounce their doom I muſt be ſent.</l>
                  <l>I know O Lord what theſe men now do find</l>
                  <l>That thou art gracious mercifull and kind</l>
                  <l>Full ſlack thou art, and ſlow pac'd unto wrath</l>
                  <l>But winged ſpeed always thy mercy hath;</l>
                  <l>And if a people truly do lament,</l>
                  <l>For ſin, and do reform: thou wilt repent.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104634:37"/>
                  <l>Conſid'ring then it would not be avoided</l>
                  <l>By heathen ones thy word would be derided</l>
                  <l>And my ambaſſage too, they would deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>And ſay I thundred out a heap of lies;</l>
                  <l>For which ſo ſaying I muſt bear the blame</l>
                  <l>And be cal'd prophet falſe, to my great ſhame:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is the reaſon, it ſeems right to mee</l>
                  <l>Why formerly to <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> I did flee:</l>
                  <l>And thou haſt judg'd it for a heinous crime,</l>
                  <l>But whoſe the fault, whether 'tis thine or mine.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things ſo ſadly do my ſpirits grieve</l>
                  <l>No earthly thing O Lord will me releive:</l>
                  <l>It is far better for me for to dye,</l>
                  <l>And in the duſt in ſilent darkneſs lye</l>
                  <l>Then longer live: ſith nothing but diſgrace</l>
                  <l>My portion is whilſt I am in this place;</l>
                  <l>I do beſeech thee let my life expire</l>
                  <l>And take it from me that is my deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus when fond paſſion ſways and goes uncurb'd</l>
                  <l>The minds of men thereby are ſoon diſturb'd</l>
                  <l>Soon out of order gotten out of frame,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh chooſing death rather then life; becauſe God did not act according to his mind.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>They glory in the things ſhould be their ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Lord in patience all this while did bear</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Jonah's</hi> angry paſſion: and did hear</l>
                  <l>His words reflecting on his Majeſty</l>
                  <l>Yet like a loving father paſſes by</l>
                  <l>His great offence: ſeeing him fraiſ and weak</l>
                  <l>Did thus in gentle manner to him ſpeak.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How now? what <hi>Jona?</hi> darſt thou angry prove?</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou not think it will my patience move?</l>
                  <l>How darſt thou once preſume to be ſo bold?</l>
                  <l>Doſt think with wickedneſs that I will hold?</l>
                  <l>Or doſt thou think that this is well in thee?</l>
                  <l>Oh wondrous ſtrange, what <hi>Jonah</hi> angry be?</l>
                  <l>Did not my mercy, and my juſtice ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To kill thee, els for to keep thee alive?</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou forgot, how mercy did thee ſave,</l>
                  <l>When juſtice would the whale ſhould be thy grave?</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104634:37"/>
                  <l>Mercy prevaild and thou canſt not deny it,</l>
                  <l>Then ceaſe thine anger, canſt thou juſtify it?</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou not learnd and been taught in the ſchools,</l>
                  <l>That anger reſteth in the beſt of fools.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus God in goodneſſe labour'd to convince</l>
                  <l>The pettiſh prophet of his foul offence,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and forbearance though provokt by <hi>Jonah.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Imputing all to his infirmities</l>
                  <l>As parents do to children whom they prize,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jonah</hi> is angry: yet it did not move</l>
                  <l>God to be angry cauſe he did him love:</l>
                  <l>So great is love: love, cannot finde its like</l>
                  <l>So great is love, love ſpares when it ſhould ſtrike:</l>
                  <l>So great is love not eaſy to provoke,</l>
                  <l>Love ſuffers long before it give one ſtroke;</l>
                  <l>So great is love: ſo high and broad it grows,</l>
                  <l>It covers ſins; all, multitudinous.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jonah</hi> had a longing great deſire</l>
                  <l>To ſee th'vent, when th' forty days expire</l>
                  <l>For at this time, he would not come to know</l>
                  <l>Whether God would deſtroy them yea or no;</l>
                  <l>Perhaps for one or other end God may</l>
                  <l>The execution of the judgment ſtay</l>
                  <l>For this a maxim is receiv'd of many</l>
                  <l>Forbearance never yet acquitted any.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Out of the city great and populous</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jonah</hi> departs and now away he goes</l>
                  <l>And when he came to th' eaſt ſide of the town</l>
                  <l>He goes not further but there ſits him down;</l>
                  <l>He makes a booth, and in it is his ſeat</l>
                  <l>The ſhade thereof defends him from the heat,</l>
                  <l>Untill the truth of falſhood ſhall be tride</l>
                  <l>Of his late meſſage there he doth abide;</l>
                  <l>But now perhaps ſoon after he comes thither</l>
                  <l>His booth he made begins to dry and wither,</l>
                  <l>The Country's hot, the ſun with mighty heat</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Jonah's</hi> head continually did beat</l>
                  <l>By reaſon of which heat, his ſoul is greiv'd</l>
                  <l>Then God in mercy, wills he be releiv'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104634:38"/>
                  <l>The Lord's a preſent help in time of trouble</l>
                  <l>And mercy upon mercy he doth double</l>
                  <l>And treble too:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion providing ſhelter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive <hi>Jonah.</hi>
                     </note> always in time of need</l>
                  <l>His power and pitty is put forth with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>To ſave and ſuccour his diſtreſſed ones</l>
                  <l>His bowels yearn to hear their ſighs and groans;</l>
                  <l>Fear we not then in depths of miſery,</l>
                  <l>To help us then's his oportunity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For he then brought an herb out of the earth</l>
                  <l>Turns <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſorrow into pleaſant mirth</l>
                  <l>A mighty plant he quickly made to grow</l>
                  <l>With boughs and branches on it high and low</l>
                  <l>That they might ſhade and ſhelter him all over</l>
                  <l>And from the ſcorching heat be <hi>Jonah's</hi> cover.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Under the ſhadow of it he doth reſt</l>
                  <l>Thinking thereby that he is greatly bleſt</l>
                  <l>Such great refreſhment he hath lately found,</l>
                  <l>In his new houſe ſpringing out of the ground;</l>
                  <l>He doth rejoyce he is exceeding glad</l>
                  <l>So great his joy is all the grief he had</l>
                  <l>Suſtaind by reaſon of the heat before</l>
                  <l>Seemeth as though he thought on it no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſuddain change begets experience ſad</l>
                  <l>To day he mourns that yeſterday was glad,</l>
                  <l>His ſuddain joys are turn'd to ſuddain greif,</l>
                  <l>His plant it dyes, that gave him ſuch relief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For now alas before he was aware</l>
                  <l>In readineſſe a worm God did prepare</l>
                  <l>Who with his ſharp teeth and his cruel jaws,</l>
                  <l>As bit with hunger, eagerly he gnaws</l>
                  <l>Who ſmote the gourd, and now the gourd is dead</l>
                  <l>And with it <hi>Jonah's</hi> joys are withered.</l>
                  <l>Such is the nature of all earthly things</l>
                  <l>Which for a while ſo great contentment brings</l>
                  <l>They fade, they vaniſh, periſh and decay:<note place="margin">Obſerv. from the withering of <hi>Jonah's</hi> gourd, ſhewing the fickle ſtate of all things.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With winged haſte, th'are gone and paſſe away.</l>
                  <l>Th'are but a puff, a blaſt a watry bubble</l>
                  <l>That ſoon is gone: or like a fiery ſtubble</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104634:38"/>
                  <l>That in a moment, is conſum'd and paſt,</l>
                  <l>Or like a poſt, that on the way makes haſt;</l>
                  <l>Or like the dusky clouds that break before</l>
                  <l>The ſun appears and then are ſeen no more;</l>
                  <l>Or like the flower or herb or fruit that's ſown,</l>
                  <l>That wither will as ſoon as it is mown;</l>
                  <l>Or like the vapours drawn into the ayr</l>
                  <l>Or like the thing that's gone when't doth appear.</l>
                  <l>Such are the things in which men take ſuch pleaſure</l>
                  <l>And too too much account their chiefeſt treaſure</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt joys that are upon the earth</l>
                  <l>Are dying ſtill ſo ſoon as they draw breath,</l>
                  <l>To day they are injoy'd; but ere to morrow</l>
                  <l>They oft take wing and leave poor men to ſorrow;</l>
                  <l>They neither laſt nor cannot ſatisfy,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Ionah</hi> by his gourd in part did try.</l>
                  <l>The Sun aroſe and with it roſe the wind</l>
                  <l>From th' eaſtern quarter vehement, unkind,</l>
                  <l>God had prepard it to riſe wondrous high</l>
                  <l>That he might <hi>Ionah's</hi> patience further try;</l>
                  <l>The ſun and wind they both conſpire together</l>
                  <l>To make it hot and very ſoultry weather,</l>
                  <l>They beat on <hi>Ionah: Ionah</hi> he doth faint</l>
                  <l>And breaks into this paſſionate complaint.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My life's a burden to me, let me dy</l>
                  <l>For I have liv'd to ſee thee falſify</l>
                  <l>Thy word and mine which is my dayly trouble</l>
                  <l>And yet O Lord thou doſt my ſorrows double;</l>
                  <l>My body is afflicted as my minde</l>
                  <l>Then life 'tis better for me death to finde,</l>
                  <l>O let me be ſhut up within the grave</l>
                  <l>And clos'd in ſilent darkneſſe: then I have</l>
                  <l>That thing I wiſh and in my ſelf deſire,</l>
                  <l>And cannot have it till my life expire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mans days on earth moſt variouſly are ſpent</l>
                  <l>Sometimes he's pleas'd, ſometimes he's diſcontent,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate complaint upon his ſuddain change.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes his joys do mightily abound,</l>
                  <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e while again they caſt him to the ground:</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104634:39"/>
                  <l>For joy he laughs ſometimes for ſorrow weeps,</l>
                  <l>Nor reaſon nor religions bounds he keeps;</l>
                  <l>When man's tranſported with his lawleſs paſſion</l>
                  <l>Not to Gods will but his own he will faſhion</l>
                  <l>Himſelf in all things be it good or bad,</l>
                  <l>Anger, joy, ſorrow, oft makes wiſe men mad.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then God repli'd to him a ſecond time,</l>
                  <l>Mine anger might ariſe as well as thine</l>
                  <l>Then thou a greater cauſe I have beſure,</l>
                  <l>And yet my patience ſtill it doth endure;</l>
                  <l>So manifold affronts I have had fro' thee,</l>
                  <l>Where judgment might yet mercy is ſhewd to thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is this a thing worthy thy commendation?</l>
                  <l>Angry to be after this diſpenſation,</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou regard my acts of providence</l>
                  <l>Sham'd thou wouldſt be; to take ſo great offence</l>
                  <l>At ſo ſmall matter; is this well in thee</l>
                  <l>To be diſpleas'd at what is done by me?</l>
                  <l>How darſt thou let thy anger riſe ſo high</l>
                  <l>As in it wiſh ſo deſperately to dy?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus God with <hi>Ionah</hi> argueth the caſe</l>
                  <l>To bring his ſoul again into its place</l>
                  <l>When we run from him he ſtill ſeeketh us,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from Gods reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo lovingly with <hi>Jonah</hi> to bring his ſoul into its place and ſet him ſtraight again.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſayth return again; why is it thus?</l>
                  <l>When man is minding naught but ſelf concerns</l>
                  <l>The wiſe and gracious God full ſoon diſcerns</l>
                  <l>His ſwift deſtruction uſherd in a pace,</l>
                  <l>If not prevented by his ſpecial grace.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jonah</hi> anſw'ring ſaid to God again</l>
                  <l>My angry paſſion I will ſtill maintain:</l>
                  <l>My cauſe is good I can it juſtify,</l>
                  <l>And if I angry be untill I dye</l>
                  <l>Untill my ſoul is from my body going</l>
                  <l>'Tis well, and weldone by me for ſo doing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gods dealings whether they are rough or mild</l>
                  <l>Doth little good when paſſion groweth wilde,<note place="margin">Obſerv. from <hi>Jonah's</hi> ill uſe of Gods gentle dealing with him; anſwering foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly again.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor ſharp reproof nor exhortation kind,</l>
                  <l>Will any kindly entertainment find:</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:104634:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Where luſt uncurbed goes, and gets the reynes</l>
                  <l>It bootleſs proveth for to uſe the means</l>
                  <l>Of betterment; men thereby rather turn</l>
                  <l>Away from God and at his counſell ſpurn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Once more the Lord repli'd, and to him ſaid</l>
                  <l>With thy own practiſe I will thee upbraid,</l>
                  <l>What? haſt thou not for thy own ſelf much cared?</l>
                  <l>And glad hadſt been; if I the gourd had ſpared</l>
                  <l>Had'ſt not thou pitty on that fading thing?</l>
                  <l>Which I out of the earths-large-womb did bring</l>
                  <l>Up in one night without the help of day,</l>
                  <l>And in one night it periſht quite away:</l>
                  <l>Thy labour on it thou didſt not beſtow</l>
                  <l>No art nor skill of thine did make it grow.</l>
                  <l>This plant this gourd, fain thou wodſt have preſervd</l>
                  <l>It pleaſant was to thee: and ſo deſerv'd</l>
                  <l>Thy care and diligence to nouriſh it</l>
                  <l>Sith in its ſhade thou didſt delighted ſit:</l>
                  <l>Which was a thing of very ſmall renown</l>
                  <l>Compared with that great Aſſirian town.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What reaſon then that I ſhould not take pitty?</l>
                  <l>Upon that famous, great, populous City,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the little ones beſides the old</l>
                  <l>Were more then ſixſcore thouſand fully told,</l>
                  <l>All perſons for their age unapt to learn</l>
                  <l>'Twixt right and left hand they cannot diſcern.</l>
                  <l>The cattels much, that doth about it feed,</l>
                  <l>To be prefer'd before a ſtinking weed;</l>
                  <l>I made them for my ſervice and my uſe</l>
                  <l>Yet me they did provoke by their abuſe;</l>
                  <l>To threaten judgment therefore thou waſt ſent;</l>
                  <l>And when they heatd, they fear'd and did repent.</l>
                  <l>How could I chuſe, but on them pitty take?</l>
                  <l>And ſhew them favour for my mercy ſake;</l>
                  <l>For why in mercy thou knowſt I abound</l>
                  <l>And not them only but thy ſelf haſt found,</l>
                  <l>As great forbearance at my gentle hand,</l>
                  <l>When thou rebeld againſt my juſt command;</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:104634:40"/>
                  <l>And now like to a frantick furious fool</l>
                  <l>Art diſcontent becauſe I do not rule</l>
                  <l>According to thy pleaſure: not thy will</l>
                  <l>But mine be done: thou oughtſt it to fulfill;</l>
                  <l>Then up, be gone, and get thee home with ſhame</l>
                  <l>And ſtudy more to know my glorious name:</l>
                  <l>Regard my voice, and anſwer when I call thee,</l>
                  <l>And ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
